[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "________ is not use to make Portland Cement (PC).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcareous Rocks",
            "b) Argillocalcareous Rocks",
            "c) Argillaceous Rocks",
            "d) Sand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sand is mixed with Cement to make concrete instead of making cement. Materials which we get from these 3 rocks are useful to make healty PC."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which one doesn’t comes under Calcareous Rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limestone",
            "b) Cement rock",
            "c) Chalk",
            "d) Marine shell deposits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cement Rock comes in Argillocalcareous Rocks. And Calcareous Rocks have Limestone, Marl, Chalk, Marine Shell Deposits."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of CLINKER in PC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-3%",
            "b) 4-6%",
            "c) 2-6%",
            "d) 3-5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Portland cement is made by mixing substances containing CaCO3 with substances containing SiO2, Al2O3, Fe2O3 and heating them to a clinker which is subsequently ground to powder and mixed with 2-6 % gypsum."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "As the materials pass through the kiln their temperature is rised upto ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1300-1600 °C",
            "b) 1100-1500 °C",
            "c) 1300-1500 °C",
            "d) 1100-1600 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 1300-1600 °C is the best range to melt the raw materials for a healty PC. Below 1300 °C the materials whcih we added to make PC won’t melt perfectly and the result will be unhealty PC."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "What is the diameter and length of the kiln respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6m and 200m",
            "b) 200m and 6m",
            "c) 6m and 6m",
            "d) 200m and 200m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: They are produced in a range of sizes and units with diameters up to 6 m and lengths up to 200 m have been made."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the range of CaCO3 in Argillocalcareous Rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) >75%",
            "b) 40-75%",
            "c) <45%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the standard value for in Argillocalcareous Rocks (40-75% CaCO3 such as clayey limestone, clayey marl)."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What is the diameter of Clinker for making of Portland Cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .15-5 cm",
            "b) .15-5 m",
            "c) .3-4 cm",
            "d) .3-4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cement kilns are used for the pyroprocessing stage of manufacture of Portland and other types of hydraulic cement, in which calcium carbonate reacts with silica-bearing minerals to form a mixture of calcium silicates."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "What is the composition of making the Mortar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P.C. + Water",
            "b) P.C. + Water + Sand",
            "c) P.C. + Water + Sand + Gravel",
            "d) Water + Sand + Gravel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the materials pass through the kiln their temperature is rised upto 1300-1600 °C. The process of heating is named as “burning”. The output is known as “clinker” which is 0.15-5 cm in diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "What is wet process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their dry state",
            "b) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their medium state",
            "c) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their wet state",
            "d) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their overheated state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their wet state is called wet process and grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their dry state is called dry process."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "What is the moisture content in slurry for wet process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35-50%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 40-45%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moisture content in slurry for wet process is 35-50%. 12% is the moisture content for dry process."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Among the below statement, which one is correct for wet process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The amount of heat required is high, so the required fuel amount is high",
            "b) The amount of heat required is lesser, so the required fuel amount is less",
            "c) The amount of heat required is high, so the required fuel amount is less",
            "d) The amount of heat required is less, so the required fuel amount is high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The kiln size is bigger for wet process than for dry process to manufacture the cement because much of the kiln’s length was used up for the drying process."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "The slurry with the desired lime content passes into the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clinker",
            "b) Rotary kiln",
            "c) Slurry tank",
            "d) Cement silo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amount of heat required is higher, so the required fuel amount is higher for wet  process and vice-versa for dry process."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "The slurry, in its movement down the kiln, encounters a progressively higher temperature. At first, the water is driven off and ___  is liberated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SiO2",
            "b) CO2",
            "c) Gypsum",
            "d) CaO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slurry with the desired lime content passes into the rotary kiln up to 8 m in diameter and length 230m."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "When chalk is used _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is finely broken up and dispersed in water in a wash mill",
            "b) It has to be blasted, then crushed, usually in two progressively smaller crushers",
            "c) It is sieved and fed into a rotating dish called a granulator",
            "d) The raw materials are crushed and fed into a grinding mill, where they are dried and reduced into fine powder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At 900°C limestone decomposes, CaCO3.CaO + CO2 (endothermic reaction) CO2 is swept away by current air."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "In the wet process, the kiln is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal",
            "b) Vertical",
            "c) Slightly inclined with vertical",
            "d) Slightly inclined with horizontal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In wet process, raw materials can be mixed easily and therefore we don’t need any extra energy and due to this machinery and equipments do not need much maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "In the wet process of cement manufacturing raw material is heated to about _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 650-900 °C",
            "b) 900-1300 °C",
            "c) 1300-1450 °C",
            "d) 900-1050 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When chalk is used, it is finely broken up and dispersed in water in a wash mill. Similarly, the clay is also broken up and mixed with water, usually in a similar wash mill."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What is dry process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their dry state",
            "b) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their wet state",
            "c) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their medium state",
            "d) Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their super dry state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their dry state is known as dry process and grinding and mixing of the raw materials in their wet state is known as wet process."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The raw materials is so hard (solid) that they _________ disintegrate by water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) do",
            "b) may be",
            "c) do not",
            "d) may or may not"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The raw materials is so hard that they do not differentiate by water because the water might freeze in the mixture."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "To obtain cement dry powder, lime stones and shales or their slurry, is burnt in a rotary kiln at a temperature between ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1100° and 1200°C",
            "b) 1200° and 1300°C",
            "c) 1300° and 1400°C",
            "d) 1400° and 1500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this process calcareous material such as lime stone (calcium carbonate) and argillaceous material such as clay are ground separately to fine powder in the absence of water and then are mixed together in the desired proportions."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "The blended meal is sieved and fed into a rotating dish called a ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clinker",
            "b) Kiln",
            "c) Granulator",
            "d) Raw meal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The blended meal is sieved and fed into a rotating dish called a granulator, water weighing about 12% of the meal being added at the same time."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "What is the moisture content in slurry for dry process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35-50%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 40-45%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 12% is the moisture content in slurry for dry process. The moisture content in slurry for wet process is 35-50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Among the below statement, which one is correct for dry process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The amount of heat required is high, so the required fuel amount is high",
            "b) The amount of heat required is less, so the required fuel amount is less",
            "c) The amount of heat required is high, so the required fuel amount is less",
            "d) The amount of heat required is less, so the required fuel amount is high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of heat required is lesser, so the required fuel amount is less for dry process and vice-versa for wet process."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "What is the diameter of hard pellets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm",
            "b) 12mm",
            "c) 15mm",
            "d) 18mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In dry process, raw materials cannot be mixed easily and therefore we need any extra energy and due to this machinery and equipments do need much maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gypsum in cement decreases the setting time",
            "b) The first compound of cement which reacts with water is C2S",
            "c) Bulking of sand is less when its particles are fine",
            "d) Dry process is less economically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hard pellets about 15 mm in diameter are formed. The pellets are baked hard in a pre-heating grate by means of hot gases from the kiln."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of cement produced in dry process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85%",
            "b) 70%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Any residual would have a negative effect on the setting. The gypsum should be mixed under vacuum, if possible, and to the exact water/powder ratio. The gypsum should be sprinkled into the water."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What is hydration of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical reaction of cement with acid",
            "b) Chemical reaction of cement with water",
            "c) Chemical reaction of cement with base",
            "d) Chemical reaction of cement with salt, and acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As water comes into contact with cement particles, hydration reactions immediately starts at the surface of the particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "As the hydration proceeds the deposits of hydrated products on the original cement grains makes the diffusion of water to unhydrated nucleus ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy",
            "b) Very difficult",
            "c) Very easy",
            "d) Average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is difficult thus the rate of hydration decreases with time & as result hydration may take several years."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "The development of first 28 days strength is on account of the hydration of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) C2S",
            "b) C3S",
            "c) C3A",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Higher C3S→higher early strength-higher heat generation (roads, cold environments). Higher CS→lower early strength-lower heat generation (dams)."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which compound is liberates higher heat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C2S",
            "b) C3S",
            "c) C3A",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: C3S having a faster rate of reaction accompanied by greater heat generation developes early strength of the paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which compound is liberates lower heat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C2S",
            "b) C3S",
            "c) C3A",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C2S hydrates & hardens slowly so results in less heat generation & developes most of the ultimate strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which compound may lead to a rapid stiffening of the paste with a large amount of the heat generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C2S",
            "b) C3S",
            "c) C3A",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: C3A is characteristically fast reacting with water & may lead to a rapid stiffening of the paste with a large amount of the heat generation (Flash-Set)-(Quick-Set)."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "In order to prevent this rapid reaction _______ is added to the clinker.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C4AF",
            "b) Gypsum",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Extra cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to prevent this rapid reaction gypsum is added to the clinker. Gypsum, C3A&water react to form relatively insoluble Calcium-Sulfo-Aluminates."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which chemical compostion has highest content in OPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alumina",
            "b) Silica",
            "c) Lime",
            "d) Iron Oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lime forms nearly two-third (2/3) of the cement. Therefore sufficient quantity of the lime must be in the raw materials for the manufacturing of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Excess in lime causes _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cement to shrink and integrate",
            "b) The cement to shrink and disintegrate",
            "c) The cement to expand and integrate",
            "d) The cement to expand and disintegrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sufficient quantity of lime forms di-calcium silicate (C2SiO2) and tri-calcium silicate in the manufacturing of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Silica in excess causes ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cement to set slowly",
            "b) The cement to set quickly",
            "c) The cement to expand",
            "d) The cement to disintegrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silica gives strength to the cement. Silica in excess causes the cement to set slowly."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Alumina in excess causes _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduces the strength of the cement",
            "b) Inceases the strength of the cement",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Sometimes increase or decrease the strength of the cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alumina supports to set quickly to the cement. It also lowers the clinkering temperature. Alumina in excess reduces the strength of the cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which compound gives the colour to the cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lime",
            "b) Silica",
            "c) Iron Oxide",
            "d) Alumina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Iron oxide pigments are in the form of particles ranging approximately from 0.1 to 1.0 micron. The difference in color between one pigment and another is due to the shape and surface structure of the particle."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which cement contains high percentage of C3S and less percentage of C2S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Ordinary Portland Cement",
            "c) Quick Setting Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This cement contains high percentage of C3S and less percentage of C3S. This is infact high early strength cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "When concrete is to be laid under water ___________ is to used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Ordinary Portland Cement",
            "c) Quick Setting Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When concrete is to be laid under water, quick setting cement is to used. This cement is manufactured by adding small percentage of aluminum sulphate (Al2SO4) which accelerates the setting action."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct for Low Heat Cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suitable for use in cold weather areas",
            "b) Heat of hydration is reduced by tri calcium aluminate content",
            "c) This cement requires longer period of curing",
            "d) This cement contains high aluminate %age usually between 35-55%."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this cement the heat of hydration is reduced by tri calcium aluminate content. It contains less percentage of lime than ordinary port land cement. It is used for mass concrete works such as dams etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which cement is used in sewage and water treatment plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Low Heat Cement",
            "c) Sulphate Resisting Cement",
            "d) Quick Setting Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cement with composition has very good resistance to sulphate attack. This type of cement is used in the construction of foundation in soil where subsoil contains very high proportions of sulphate."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which cement is used for mainly building construction where strength required with age?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Low Heat Cement",
            "c) Portland Pozzolana Cement",
            "d) Quick Setting Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It gains very high compressive strength with age unlike other cement and it is very cheap and affordable."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which cement is used for artificial marble?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Sulphate Resisting Cement",
            "c) Coloured Cement",
            "d) Quick Setting Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the name suggests, it is used where coloured cement required for any aesthetic purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which cement is used to create bond with old concrete surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Expansive Cement",
            "c) Sulphate Resisting Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the name suggests, it expands and increases in volume while settled. It is used to avoid shrinkage of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which cement is used to store for longer duration in wet climatic conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expansive Cement",
            "b) Ordinary Portland cement",
            "c) Hydrophobic Cement",
            "d) Quick Setting Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This type of cement is manufactured by mixing admixtures like petrolatum, napthalene soap which forms layer and act as water repellent."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which cement used in frost resistance concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) OPC",
            "b) PPC",
            "c) AEC",
            "d) QSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is used to fill up the gap in concrete which are produced by excessive amount of water during casting (later evaporated and leave the gap)."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which cement is used for the construction of water-retaining structure like tanks, reservoirs, retaining walls, swimming pools, dams, bridges, piers etc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waterproof Portland cement",
            "b) Colored Cement",
            "c) High Alumina Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This cement is prepared by mixing with OPC or rapid hardening cement with a small percentage of some metal stearates at the time of mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "____ cement is used for formwork that can be removed earlier and reused in other areas which save the cost of formwork.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Colored Cement",
            "c) High Alumina Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rapid hardening cement is used where the formwork can be removed earlier and reused in other areas which save the cost of formwork. This cement can be used in prefabricated concrete construction, road works, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which cement is mainly used for interior and exterior decorative works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid Hardening Cement",
            "b) Colored Cement",
            "c) High Alumina Cement",
            "d) Low Heat Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This Cement is produced by adding 5- 10% mineral pigments with Portland cement during the time of grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "How many times in each layer of concrete rodded in a slump cone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 12 to 15",
            "d) 35 to 65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each time, each layer is tamped 25 times with a 2 ft (600 mm)-long bullet-nosed metal rod measuring 5/8 in (16 mm) in diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "How many layers of concrete are placed to fill a slump cone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 layers",
            "b) 3 equal layers by volume",
            "c) 3 equal layers by height",
            "d) 5 layers by volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fill the mold 12 inches high in the shape of the frustum of a cone that is 8 inches in diameter at the bottom and 4 inches in diameter at the top. Then fill it in three equal layers by volume, not by height."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "To measure the concrete temperature, the stem of the thermometer must be kept by at least ___ inches of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is good to remove the voids from the concrete to increase its strength. Therefore, tapping is needed to remove the remaining voids from the slump cone."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "In the soundness test a specimen of hardened cement paste is ___ for a fixed time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze",
            "b) Dry",
            "c) Boiled",
            "d) Dipped in water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stem of the thermometer should be surrounded by at least 3 inches of the concrete for better reading."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "If L1=Measurement taken after 24 hours of immersion in water at a temp. of 27 ± 20oC and L2=Measurement taken after 3 hours of immersion in water at boiling temperature. Then what is soundness of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L1+L2",
            "b) L1/L2",
            "c) L1-L2",
            "d) L1*L2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A specimen of hardened cement paste is boiled for a fixed time so that if there is any tendency of increase or decrease in size can be detected."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "To determine the fineness of cement ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grain size is smaller than specified mesh size",
            "b) Grain size is larger than specified mesh size",
            "c) Grain size is equal to specified mesh size",
            "d) Grain size is 1mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: L1-L2 is the formula to calculate the soundness of cement. First take the reading after immersion in water then measure it after 3 hours of immersion in boiling water."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The apparatus used are ___ IS Sieve, Balance capable of weighing 10g to the nearest 10mg.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90μm",
            "b) 45μm",
            "c) 22.5μm",
            "d) 14μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To determine the fineness of cement by dry sieving as per IS: 4031 (Part 1) – 1996. The principle of this is that we determine the proportion of cement whose grain size is larger than the specified mesh size."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "What is the amount of water required to give the paste normal consistency for consistency test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .78 times",
            "b) .79 times",
            "c) .77 times",
            "d) .76 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The apparatus used are 90μm IS Sieve, Balance capable of weighing 10g to the nearest 10mg, A nylon or pure bristle brush, preferably with 25 to 40mm, bristle, for cleaning the sieve."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which apparatus is generally used to measure the soundness of the cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vicat Apparatus",
            "b) Le-Chatelier apparatus",
            "c) Soundness meter",
            "d) Duff Abrams apparatus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prepare a paste by adding 0.78 times the water required to give a paste of standard consistency (i.e. 0.78P)."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Why  do we need Standard Consistency Test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the quality of cement",
            "b) To determine the quality of water",
            "c) To determine the quality of mixed concrete",
            "d) To determine the strength of concrete block"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This test is performed to determine the quantity of water required to produce a cement paste of standard or normal consistency."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "What is standard consistency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consistency which permits the Vicat’s plunger",
            "b) Ability of cement to maintain a constant volume",
            "c) Durability in sea water",
            "d) Free lime content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Standard consistency of cement paste may be defined as the consistency which permits the Vicat’s plunger (10 mm, 40 to 50 mm in length) to penetrate to a point 5 mm to 7 mm from the bottom ( or 35 mm to 33 mm from top) of Vicat mould."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "When the cement paste is tested within the gauging time. Here what is the value of gauging time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 to 5 minutes",
            "b) 3 to 5 hours",
            "c) 24 minutes",
            "d) 24 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the cement paste is tested within the gauging time (3 to 5 minutes) after the cement is thoroughly mixed with water."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "How many moulds required for the compression strength test of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this test, three moulds of (face area 50 cm2) are prepared and cured under standard  temperature conditions and each cube tested by placing it between movable jaws of the compressive strength testing machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Which of the following option is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard consistency (%) = (wt of water added/ wt of cement) *100",
            "b) Standard consistency (%) = (wt of water added- wt of cement) *100",
            "c) Standard consistency = (wt of water added/ wt of cement) *100",
            "d) Standard consistency (%) = (wt cement/ wt of water) *100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To determine the standard consistency, we need to divide the weight of water to cement and then multiply it with 100 to get the percentage of standard consistency."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": " Standard consistency of cement is tested by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vicat apparatus",
            "b) Le Chatalier apparatus",
            "c) Soundness meter",
            "d) Duff Abrams apparatus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard consistency of a cement paste is defined as that consistency which will allow the vicat’s plunger to penetrate to a point 5 to 7mm from the bottom of the vicat mould."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Calculate standard consistency(%) when 100 ml of water is added in 1000 g of cement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Standard consistency (%) = (wt of water added/ wt of cement) *100\n= 100/1000*100\n= 10. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "For making cement paste, what is the amount of water we need?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25% water by weight of dry cement",
            "b) 30% water by weight of dry cement",
            "c) 78% water by weight of dry cement",
            "d) 80% water by weight of dry cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 25% water by weight of dry cement thoroughly to get a cement paste. Total time taken to obtain thoroughly mixed water cement paste. "
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "What is the normal consistency for OPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26 to 33%",
            "b) 20 to 35%",
            "c) 26 to 50%",
            "d) 33 to 55%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a cement paste the standard consistency is measured by flow table test which ranges from 26 to 33%. "
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "The relative humidity of laboratory should be ___________ for standard consistency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65 ± 5%",
            "b) 27 ± 2%",
            "c) 50 ± 5%",
            "d) 45 ± 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unless otherwise specified this test shall be conducted at a temperature 27 + 20 C and the relative humidity of laboratory should be 65 + 5%. "
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "In cement hardening process ___________ instants are very important.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cement hardening process, two instants are very important, i.e. initial setting and final setting."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the initial setting time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The time at which cement paste loses its plasticity",
            "b) The time at which cement paste loses its elasticity",
            "c) The time at which cement paste gains its plasticity",
            "d) The time at which cement paste gains its elasticity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time at which cement paste loses its plasticity is known as initial setting time of the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Initial setting time of OPC should not be less than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 minutes",
            "b) 30 minutes",
            "c) 28 minutes",
            "d) 1 hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  As per IS specification, the minimum initial setting time is 30 minutes for ordinary portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Final setting time of cement should not be more than _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 hour",
            "b) 2 hours",
            "c) 5 hours",
            "d) 10 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per IS specification, the maximum final setting time for all type of cement is 10 hours."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "In the soundness test, the whole assembly is immersed in water for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 minutes",
            "b) 1 hour",
            "c) 24 hours",
            "d) 48 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Submerge the whole assembly immediately in water at a temperature of 27oC ±  2oC and keep it there for 24 hour for better results."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "What is the final setting time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The time at which cement paste loses its plasticity",
            "b) The time to reach that stage at which cement paste loses its elasticity",
            "c) The time at which cement paste gains its plasticity",
            "d) The time when cement paste becomes hardened"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The final setting is defined as the time taken to reach the cement paste to become into a hardened mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Initial setting time of Low Heat Cement should not be less than _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 minutes",
            "b) 30 minutes",
            "c) 60 minutes",
            "d) 1 hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per IS specification, the minimum initial setting time is 60 minutes for low heat cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "If t1=Time at which water is first added to cement, t2=Time when needle fails to penetrate 5 mm to 7 mm from bottom of the mould, t3=Time when the needle makes an impression but the attachment fails to do so, then what is initial setting time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) t2-t1",
            "b) t2+t1",
            "c) t3-t1",
            "d) 2*t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: t2-t1 is the formula to determine the value of the initial setting time of concrete for further process."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "If t1=Time at which water is first added to cement, t2=Time when needle fails to penetrate 5 mm to 7 mm from bottom of the mould, t3=Time when the needle makes an impression but the attachment fails to do so, then what is final setting time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) t2-t1",
            "b) t2+t1",
            "c) t3-t1",
            "d) 2*t1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: t3-t1 is the formula to determine the value of the final setting time of concrete for further process."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of a measuring cylinder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10ml",
            "b) 50ml",
            "c) 100ml",
            "d) 1000ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The capacity of the measuring cylinder is 100 ml with the least count of 1 ml for the setting time test."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Insoluble Residue mainly comes from which compound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lime",
            "b) Soda",
            "c) Silica",
            "d) Alumina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Portland cement is composed of four major oxides ((CaO, SiO2, Al2O3, Fe2O32O & K2O in P.C.?\na) =.6%\nb) >6%\nc) <6%\nd) 0\nView AnswerAnswer: c\nExplanation: Alkalies (Na2O & K2O) may cause some dificulties if the cement is used with certain types of reactive aggregates in making concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Loss on Ignition (L.O.I.) is the loss in weight of cement after being heated to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000°C",
            "b) 100°C",
            "c) 500°C",
            "d) 1500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "On cooling below 1250oC, C3S decomposes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast",
            "b) Slowly",
            "c) Never",
            "d) Depends on the conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Insoluble Residue is that fraction of cement which is insoluble in HCl. It comes mainly from the silica which has not reacted to form compounds during the burning process in the kiln."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Gypsum reacts with ____________ to form calcium sulfo aluminates and calcium sulfo ferrite.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C4AF",
            "b) CF4",
            "c) SO3",
            "d) CaO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It indicates the prehydration or carbonation due to prolonged or improper storage of cement & clinker."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "C3 S and C2S require approximately the _____________ amount of water for hydration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) More",
            "c) Less",
            "d) Depends on the paste"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C4AF is not a true compound. The ferrite phase ranges from C2AF to C6AF. *C4AF represents an average."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "According to geological origin, aggregates is/are classified into __________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 2 types of aggregates based on geological origin. They are natural aggregates and artificial aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "According to size, aggregates is/are classified into __________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 4 types of aggregates based on size. They are fine aggregates, coarse aggregates, all in aggregates and single size aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "What is the total percentage of aggregates in concrete by volume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-60%",
            "b) 60-75%",
            "c) 85%",
            "d) 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aggregates, which account for 60-75% of the total volume of concrete, are divided into 2 categories."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is the size of fine aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.75mm",
            "b) < 4.75mm",
            "c) > 4.75mm",
            "d) 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The size of the fine aggregates is less than 4.75mm because it passes from 4.75 mm sieve at its lowest so there is no chance for more than 4.75mm in its size."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What is the size of coarse aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.75mm",
            "b) < 4.75mm",
            "c) > 4.75mm",
            "d) 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The size of the fine aggregates is less than 4.75mm because it passes from 4.75 mm sieve but the aggregates which don’t pass through it are coarse aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Crushed stone, gravel and ordinary sand are examples of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lightweight aggregate",
            "b) Normal-weight aggregate",
            "c) Heavy-weight aggregate",
            "d) Both Normal-weight aggregate and Heavy-weight aggregate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crushed stone, gravel and ordinary sand are examples of normal weight aggregate. They are commonly used in manufacture of normal weight concrete, asphalt concrete and roadway sub-base. "
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Aggregate crushed before the application of full load of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10ton",
            "b) 20ton",
            "c) 30ton",
            "d) 40ton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Possessing well defined edges formed at the intersection of roughly planar faces."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Natural aggregates come in which category?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Based on size",
            "b) Based on origin",
            "c) Based on density",
            "d) Based on shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The word natural itself says that it comes from nature which comes in origin. And there are 2 types of aggregates in based on origin i.e. natural and artificial aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "What are artificial aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Those who obtained from river beds",
            "b) Those who are manufactured naturally",
            "c) Those who are mechanically obtained",
            "d) Who has smooth surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Natural aggregate are those from the river beds, river sand and ex-mines. They are generally normally rounded in shape and have smooth surface texture."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The bulk density of aggregates does not depend upon ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size and shape of aggregates",
            "b) Specific gravity of aggregates",
            "c) Grading of aggregates",
            "d) Size and shape of the container"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Artificial aggregate are those obtained by mechanically crushing rocks, boulders, or cobbles. Normally angular in shape and have rough surface texture."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "An aggregate is said to be flaky if its least dimension is less than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/5th of mean dimension",
            "b) 2/5th of mean dimension",
            "c) 3/5th of mean dimension",
            "d) 4/5th of mean dimension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bulk density is depends on the properties of the aggregates not of the container. Size, shape, Specific gravity, grading are the properties of aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The light weight aggregates are obtained from",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentary rocks",
            "b) Metamorphic rocks",
            "c) Igneous rocks",
            "d) Volcanic source"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An aggregate is said to be flaky if its least dimension is less than 3/5th of mean dimension."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "The standard sand now a days used in India, is obtained from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ennore (Madras)",
            "b) Jaipur",
            "c) Jullundur (Punjab)",
            "d) Hyderabad"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  For making light weight masonry blocks (to improved their thermal and insulating properties and nailing characteristic)."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "For the construction of cement concrete floor, the maximum permissible size of aggregate is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.75mm",
            "b) 8mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) 15mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the people are used Ennore sand for its good strength and other properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Generally heavy weight aggregate obtained from ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minerals ores",
            "b) Palm oil shell",
            "c) Sand",
            "d) Crushed stone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 40 mm for massive works like dams, retaining walls, etc. 20 mm for Reinforced member. 10 mm for floors."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Pick up the most appropriate statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulk density of normal weight aggregate is 1600 kg/m3",
            "b) Bulk density of normal weight aggregate is 2000 kg/m3",
            "c) Bulk density of normal weight aggregate is 1000 kg/m3",
            "d) Bulk density of normal weight aggregate is 1250 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bulk density of normal weight aggregate is around 1520 to 1680 kg/m3 and the rest of the options don’t come under that range."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The 28 days cube strength of mass concrete using aggregates of maximum size 5 cm for gravity dams should be _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between 150 to 300 kg/cm2",
            "b) Between 350 to 600 kg/cm2",
            "c) Between 150 to 400 kg/cm2",
            "d) Less than 200 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 28 days cube strength of mass concrete using aggregates of maximum size 5 cm for gravity dams should be less than 200 kg/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "The unit weight of heavy weight concrete varies from __________ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000",
            "b) 2400",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The unit weight of heavy weight concrete varies from 2400 kg/m3 with sp.gr range from 4.0 to 4.6. (eg: mineral ore sand barite)."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "S.I. unit of bulk density is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) kg/l",
            "b) g/ml",
            "c) kg/ml",
            "d) g/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of crushed aggregates may results in 10 to 20% higher compressive strength due to development of stronger aggregate-mortar bond."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is void ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – (bulk density/apparent sp gr)",
            "b) (bulk density/apparent sp gr) – 1",
            "c) 1 – bulk density/apparent sp gr",
            "d) bulk density/apparent sp gr – 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bulk density of an aggregate is defined as the mass of material in a given volume and expressed in kg/l."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The average specific gravity of natural aggregate is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.7",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The empty space between the aggregates particles are termed as voids. And the corresponding ratio will be calculated by the given formula."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Pick up the most appropriate statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sp. Gr. = c/a-b",
            "b) Sp. Gr. = c/(a-b)",
            "c) Sp. Gr. = a-b/c",
            "d) Sp. Gr. = (a-b)/c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average specific gravity of majority of natural aggregates lies between 2.6 and 2.8."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The ratio of the mass of the aggregate dried in an oven at ___________ for 24 hours to the mass of the water occupying a volume equal to that of solid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-110oC",
            "b) 150-180oC",
            "c) 100oC",
            "d) 1500oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Specific gravity is the ratio of the density of a substance to the density of a reference substance; equivalently, it is the ratio of the mass of a substance to the mass of a reference substance for the same given volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Aggregate abrasion value is determined by__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aggregates crushing strength",
            "b) Los Angeles abrasion test",
            "c) Aggregates Impact value test",
            "d) Ten percent fine test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: First sieve the sample aggregate, aggregate passing 12.5mm sieve and retaining 10mm sieve is oven dries at 100-110oC for 3-4 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "What do you mean by bulking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The volume increase of fine aggregate due to presence of moisture content in it",
            "b) The moisture present in aggregate forms a film around each particle",
            "c) Fine aggregate shows completely realistic volume",
            "d) The state of setting someone or something apart from others"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The volume increase of fine aggregate due to presence of moisture content is known as bulking. Fine sand bulks more as compared to coarse sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of bulk if fine aggregates manufactured by extremely fine sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fine aggregate do not show any bulking when it is absolutely dry or completely saturated."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Bulking ___________ with increase in moisture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) First increase then decrease",
            "d) First decrease then increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Extremely fine sand particularly the manufactured fine aggregate bulks as much as about 40%."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Fine sand bulks __________ than coarse sand.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less",
            "b) More",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Depends on volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bulking increases with increase in moisture content upto a certain limit and beyond that the further increase in moisture content results in decrease in volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "If h = height of sand when moist and h1 is the height when saturated then what is the percentage of bulking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) {(h-h1)/h1}*100",
            "b) {(h1-h)/h1}*100",
            "c) {(h-h1)/h}*100",
            "d) {(h1-h)/h}*100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fine sand bulks more as compared to coarse sand, i.e. percentage of bulking in indirectly proportional to the size of particle."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which apparatus we don’t need to calculate the bulking of fine aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measuring cylinder",
            "b) Weighing balance",
            "c) Steel rule",
            "d) Vicat’s mould"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the formula to calculate the percentage of bulking. Percentage in bulking = {(h-h1)/h1}*100."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "What is bulking of coarse aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than sand",
            "b) Less than sand",
            "c) Equal than sand",
            "d) Negligible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vicat’s mould don’t come in use to calculate the bulking percentage because it is used to find initial and final setting time."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "If the moisture content of 5 to 10% by weight, then the bulking of sand is increased by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bulking is indirectly proportional to the particle size of the aggregates. Size of coarse aggregates is more hence negligible bulking."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "When sand is fully dry then it’s volume is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Less",
            "c) More",
            "d) Can’t say"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: With the moisture content of 5 to 10% by weight, the bulking of sand is increased by 50."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "What is soundness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soundness of cement is the property by virtue of which the cement does not undergo any appreciable expansion",
            "b) Soundness of cement is the property by virtue of which the cement does undergo any appreciable expansion",
            "c) Soundness of cement is the property by virtue of which the cement does not undergo any appreciable contraction",
            "d) Soundness of cement is the property by virtue of which the cement does undergo any appreciable contraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soundness of cement is the property by virtue of which the cement does not undergo any appreciable expansion."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which apparatus we need to find soundness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Le Chatelier",
            "b) Vicat’s apparatus",
            "c) CTM",
            "d) Pat test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This test is performed with the help of Le Chatelier apparatus as shown in figure below. It consists of a brass mould of diameter 30 mm and height 30 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Why do we need to find soundness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To detect the uncombined lime in cement",
            "b) To detect the combined lime in cement",
            "c) To detect the combined alumina in cement",
            "d) To detect the uncombined alumina in cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soundness Test on Cement. Soundness Test onCement is carried out to detect the presence of uncombined lime in cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "What is the maximum size of split?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mm",
            "b) .5mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) 2mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a split in mould and it does not exceed 0.50 mm. On either side of split, there are two indicators with pointed ends. The thickness of mould cylinder is 0.50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Le Chatelier apparatus consist of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brass mould",
            "b) Steel mould",
            "c) Aluminum mould",
            "d) Wooden mould"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Le Chatelier apparatus consist of brass mould with the diameter of 30mm and height of 30 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "When the cement paste is filled in mould and kept in water. Then what should be the temperature of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24-35°C",
            "b) 20°C",
            "c) 30-40°C",
            "d) 50°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A small weight is placed at top and the whole assembly is submerged in water for 24 hours. The temperature of water should be between 24°C to 35°C."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Expansion should not be more than _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5mm",
            "b) 10mm",
            "c) 5cm",
            "d) 10cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The difference between the two readings indicates the expansion of cement and it should not exceed 10 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "If the Y is the reading of sand surface (ml) then what is the percentage of bulking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) % of bulking {(200/Y)-2} x 100",
            "b) % of bulking {(200/Y)-1} x 100",
            "c) % of bulking {(100/Y)-2} x 100",
            "d) % of bulking {(100/Y)-1} x 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: % of bulking {(200/Y)-1} x 100. Report the percentage bulking of the sand to the nearest whole number."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "What is the size of caliper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30cm",
            "b) 50cm",
            "c) 30mm",
            "d) 40mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally the size of the caliper is 30cm with the least count of .5mm with the 100ml of measuring cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "What is the standard value of expansion for super sulphated cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm",
            "b) 5mm",
            "c) 1mm",
            "d) .5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the standard value for super sulphated cement under IS:6909-1990."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "How many principal thermal properties are there for aggregates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 3 principal thermal properties for aggregates: coefficient of thermal expansion, specific heat, thermal conductivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Coefficient of thermal expansion of concrete is __________ coefficient of thermal expansion in aggregates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) More than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coefficient of thermal expansion of concrete increases with the increase in coefficient of thermal expansion of aggregates and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "If the coefficient of thermal expansion of coarse aggregates and cement paste differs too much, then what happen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A small change in temperature may introduce",
            "b) No change",
            "c) A large change in temperature may introduce",
            "d) A small change in pressure may introduce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If it happens then a large change in temperature may introduce differential movement which may break the bond between the aggregates and the paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "If the coefficient of the two materials differ by more than 5.4 * 10-6 per oC, then?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Workability of concrete may freeze",
            "b) Durability of concrete subjected to freezing",
            "c) Durability of concrete subjected to boiling",
            "d) Workability of concrete subjected to boiling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the coefficient of the two materials differ by more than 5.4 * 10-6 per oC, then the Durability of concrete subjected to freezing and thawing may be affected."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "For majority of aggregates, the coefficient  of thermal expansion lies between approximately ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.4 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC",
            "b) 10.8 * 10-6 and 16.2 * 10-6 per oC",
            "c) 5.4 * 10-6 and 10.8 * 10-6 per oC",
            "d) 10.8 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient  of thermal expansion lies between approximately 5.4 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "For hydrated Portland cement, the coefficient of thermal expansion lies between approximately ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.4 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC",
            "b) 10.8 * 10-6 and 16.2 * 10-6 per oC",
            "c) 5.4 * 10-6 and 10.8 * 10-6 per oC",
            "d) 10.8 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient of thermal expansion for hydrated Portland cement lies between approximately 10.8 * 10-6 and 16.2 * 10-6 per oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The linear thermal coefficient of expansion lies between approximately ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.4 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC",
            "b) 10.8 * 10-6 and 16.2 * 10-6 per oC",
            "c) 5.8 * 10-6 and 14 * 10-6 per oC",
            "d) 10.8 * 10-6 and 12.6 * 10-6 per oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The linear thermal coefficient of expansion lies between approximately 5.8 * 10-6 and 14 * 10-6 per oC depending upon the type of aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The specific heat of the aggregates is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ability to conduct the heat",
            "b) The ability to insulate the heat",
            "c) Is a measure of its heat capacity",
            "d) Same as thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specific heat of the aggregates is a measure of its heat capacity and thermal conductivity is to conduct the heat."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "The thermal conductivity of the aggregates is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ability to conduct the heat",
            "b) The ability to insulate the heat",
            "c) Is a measure of its heat capacity",
            "d) Same as thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermal conductivity is the ability of the aggregates to conduct the heat."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "In crushing test, dry aggregates passing through ________ mm sieve and retained ________ mm in a cylinder.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12.5, 10",
            "b) 11.5, 10",
            "c) 12.5, 11.5",
            "d) 10, 2.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry aggregates passing through 12.5 mm sieves and retained 10 mm sieves are filled in a cylindrical measure of 11.5 mm diameter and 18 cm height in three layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "According to IS: 2386 part-IV, each layer is tamped ________ times in crushing test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each layer is tamped 25 times with at standard tamping rod. The test sample is weighed and placed in the test cylinder in three layers each layer being tamped again."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "A value less than 10 signifies an exceptionally _________ while above 35 would normally be regarded as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong aggregates, weak aggregates",
            "b) Weak aggregates, strong aggregates",
            "c) Strong aggregates, strong aggregates",
            "d) Weak aggregates, weak aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A value less than 10 signifies an exceptionally strong aggregate while above 35 would normally be regarded as weak aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Los Angeles machine consists of circular drum of internal diameter ________ mm and length ________ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 700, 700",
            "b) 520, 520",
            "c) 520, 700",
            "d) 700, 520"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Los Angeles machine consists of circular drum of internal diameter 700 mm and length 520 mm mounted on horizontal axis enabling it to be rotated."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which machine is preferred for abrasion test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vicat’s mould",
            "b) Los Angeles",
            "c) Flakiness Gauge",
            "d) Elongation Gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Los Angeles is preffered for abrasion test for carrying out the hardness property and has been standardized in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "A maximum value of _________ percent is allowed for WBM base course in Indian conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The aggregate crushing value provides a relative measure of a maximum value of 40%age is allowed for WBM base course in Indian conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Aggregates to be used for wearing course, the impact value shouldn’t exceed ________ percent.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aggregates to be used for wearing course, the impact value shouldn’t exceed 30 %. For bituminous macadam the maximum permissible value is 35 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What is the range of water absorption of aggregates used in road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5-2.9",
            "b) .1-2",
            "c) .1-2.5",
            "d) 2-2.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific gravity of aggregates normally used in road ranges from about 2.5 to 2.9. Water absorption values range from 0.1 to about 2.0 percent for aggregates normally used in road surfacing."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The loss in weight should not exceed ______________ percent when tested with sodium sulphate and ________ percent with magnesium sulphate solution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12, 18",
            "b) 18, 12",
            "c) 10, 15",
            "d) 15, 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss in weight should not exceed 12 percent when tested with sodium sulphate and 18 percent with magnesium sulphate solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "If 60% aggregates doesn’t pass through the 2.36mm sieve, then what would be the value of Aggregate impact value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60%",
            "b) 40%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aggregate impact value = (W1/W2)*100\n                                    = {(100-60)/100} * 100\n                                    = 40%. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "A maximum value of ___ percent is allowed for WBM base course in Indian conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Highway Construction and Maintenance, they prepared a graph of aggregates for stress vs strain in which stress is increasing wrt strain at first i.e. loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Aggregates to be used for wearing course, the impact value shouldn’t exceed __________ percent.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Highway Construction and Maintenance, they prepared a graph of aggregates for stress vs strain in which stress is decreasing wrt strain after a period of time i.e. unloading."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The loss in weight should not exceed _________ percent when tested with sodium sulphate and _________ percent with magnesium sulphate solution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12, 18",
            "b) 18, 12",
            "c) 10, 15",
            "d) 15, 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Highway Construction and Maintenance, they prepared a graph of aggregates for stress vs strain in which they came to a conclusion C is Permanent strain unrecovered."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water is the most important and least expensive ingredient of concrete",
            "b) Excess of water forms scum",
            "c) Less amount of water may cause honeycombing",
            "d) Mixing of water is used in the hydration of cement and provides lubrication between fine and coarse aggregates."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excess amount of water may cause honey combing and less amount of water gives high density to the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect for mixing water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suspended particles of clay and slit < .02%",
            "b) The quality of CaCl2 is restricted to 1.5%",
            "c) The pH value of water should be between 6-8",
            "d) Free vegetable oil is beneficial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Free vegetable oil is harmful but mineral oil up to 2% is beneficial to concrete for making healthy structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The vegetable oil if present in mixing for concrete __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves strength",
            "b) Reduces strength",
            "c) Gives more slump",
            "d) Gives a smooth surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If vegetable oil is present in mixing of concrete then it will reduces the strength due to more lubrication."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "The mineral oil if present in mixing for concrete __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves strength",
            "b) Reduces strength",
            "c) Gives more slump",
            "d) Gives a smooth surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mineral oil if present in mixing for concrete increases strength for the concentration up to 2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "With regard to the curing water, identify the incorrect statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curing water shouldn’t produce objectionable stains on the surface",
            "b) The presence of tannic acid and iron compounds is objectionable",
            "c) Iron and organic matter are responsible for staining",
            "d) Water is suitable for mixing is also suitable for curing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: With regard to the curing water, Iron and organic matter are responsible for staining."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "To neutralize 200 ml of sample should not require more than 10 ml of __________ normal HCI using methyl orange.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) .1",
            "c) 10",
            "d) .01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To neutralize 200 ml of sample should not require more than 10 ml of 0.1 normal HCI using methyl orange as an indicator and .1 and .01 is very slow process."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "To neutralize 200 ml sample of water should not require more than _________ ml of 0.1 normal NaOH.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To neutralize 200 ml water sample should not require more than 2 ml of 0.1N Caustic soda with more than 6 pH of the water."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of organic matter in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 3000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 200mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of organic matter in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of inorganic matter in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 3000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 3000mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of inorganic matter in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of suspended matter in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 3000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 2000mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of suspended matter in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of chlorides in water for RCC work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 1000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 1000mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of chlorides in water for RCC work."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of chlorides in water for PCC work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 1000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 2000mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of chlorides in water for PCC work."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the permissible limits for construction of sulphates in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200mg/l",
            "b) 2000mg/l",
            "c) 1000mg/l",
            "d) 500mg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 500mg/l is the standard value for the permissible limits for construction of sulphates in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Presence of acid, alkali ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases the strength",
            "b) Reduces the strength",
            "c) Do effect the concrete",
            "d) Depends upon the proportion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Salty water causes rusting problems in the steel provided in RCC work for the structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What is the maximum limit (ppm) for chlorides in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Presence of acid, alkali, industrial waste, sanitary sewage and water with sugar also reduce the strength of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "What is the maximum limit (ppm) for SO3 in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the standard value of maximum limit (ppm) for chlorides in water for construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the maximum limit (ppm) for turbidity in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the standard value of maximum limit (ppm) for Sulphur trioxide in water for construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "What is the maximum limit (ppm) for Alkali Carbonates and Bicarbonates in the water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is the standard value of maximum limit (ppm) for turbidity in water for construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "What do you mean by admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ingredients which are added to in cement before or after concrete mix",
            "b) Ingredients which are added to make aggregates healthier",
            "c) Ingredients added in cement to make it shinier",
            "d) Ingredients added in concrete to make good workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Admixtures are those ingredients in concrete other than Portland cement, water, and aggregates that are added to the mixture immediately before or after the concrete mix."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the function of admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To accelerate the initial set of concrete, to speed up the rate of development of strength at early ages",
            "b) To enhance the workability",
            "c) To reduce the segregation in grout and concrete mixers",
            "d) To retard the initial set, to keep concrete workable for a shorter time for placement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To retard the initial set, to keep concrete workable for a longer time for placement is incorrect in the above statement."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the function of admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the strength of concrete by reducing the water content and by densification of concrete",
            "b) To increase the durability of concrete to enhance its resistance to special conditions of exposure",
            "c) To increase the capillary flow of water through concrete and to increase its impermeability to liquids",
            "d) To control the alkali-aggregate expansion or alkali silica reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To decrease the capillary flow of water through concrete and to increase its impermeability to liquids is incorrect in the above statement."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following option doesn’t come in chemical admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasticizers",
            "b) Pozzolanic",
            "c) Super plasticizer",
            "d) Accelerators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pozzolanic property comes under mineral admixtures not under chemical admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Classification of admixtures are classified into ________ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Classification of admixtures are classified into 2 types i.e. chemical admixtures and mineral admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following option doesn’t come in mineral admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set retarders",
            "b) Blast Furnace Slag",
            "c) Flyash",
            "d) Silica Fume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Set retarders property comes under chemical admixtures not under mineral admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Admixtures which cause early setting, and hardening of concrete are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasticizers",
            "b) Retarders",
            "c) Super plasticizer",
            "d) Accelerators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Accelerators helps the admixtures in causing early setting time and hardened the concrete. "
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Mid-range water reducers result in at least _________ %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mid-range water reducers result in at least 8%. Mid-range water reducers provide more consistent setting times than standard water reducers."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "What is the main function of set retarders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase curing rate",
            "b) Slows curing rate",
            "c) Improves workability at low w/c ratio",
            "d) Speeds up start of finishing operations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Used to counteract hot weather conditions that cause increased rate of hardening. This makes placing and finishing difficult."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Super plasticizers reduce water requirement by ___________ %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12-30",
            "b) 10-15",
            "c) 30-42",
            "d) 48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Super plasticizers reduce water requirement by 12-30 %. Makes mix highly fluid and can be placed with little or no vibration or compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Damp proofing is done with a __________ based mixture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Tar",
            "c) Rubber",
            "d) Lead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Damp proofing is done with a tar based mixture, designed to help discourage water from adhering to, or penetrating, the material’s surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Damp proofing __________ the process of water absorption.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Slows",
            "c) Doesn’t effect",
            "d) Depends on the mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Damp proofing is good for slowing down the rate at which moisture is absorbed."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Damp proofing __________ resist water well enough.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Does",
            "b) Does not",
            "c) Doesn’t effect",
            "d) Depends on the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Damp proofing is cheaper in the beginning, but leads to more expensive problems later on as compared to water proofing."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "DPC _________ effective used in concretes that are in contact with water under pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Does",
            "b) Doesn’t",
            "c) Doesn’t effect",
            "d) Depends on the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the surface has only been damp proofed, the cracks and crevices are also present in the coating of the damp proofing material."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Nomenclature of water proofing agent.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PC",
            "b) KIM",
            "c) PCKIM",
            "d) WP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Damp proofing does not resist water well enough to prevent oversaturation from ground water, or excessive and constant humidity."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The addition of the admixture to the mix __________ the surface tension.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lowers",
            "b) Higher",
            "c) Don’t affect",
            "d) No change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many so-called damp proofers are not effective, especially when used in concretes that are in contact with water under pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Entrapped air normally exists in the form of relatively _________ air voids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Absent",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nomenclature of water proofing agent is KIM and PC is the nomenclature of Portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "What is water proofing admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water repellent materials",
            "b) Water fair material",
            "c) Water absorption material",
            "d) Water adsorption material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Water proofing admixtures are available in powder, paste or liquid form and may consist of pore filling or water repellent materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which one is not a chemically active pore filling material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicate of soda",
            "b) Aluminium",
            "c) Chalk",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Water proofing admixtures are available in powder, paste or liquid form. It won’t be available un gaseous form."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which one is not a chemically inactive pore filling material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Chalk",
            "c) Talc",
            "d) Fullers earth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemically active pore filling materials: silicate of soda, aluminium, zinc sulphates and calcium chloride."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Chemically active pore fillers __________ the setting of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retards",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Accelerates",
            "d) No change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemically inactive filling material: chalk, fullers earth and talc. And aluminium is active filling material."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Chemically inactive pore fillers __________ the workability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Don’t affect",
            "d) Improve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemically active pore fillers accelerate the setting of concrete and thus render the concrete more impervious at early age."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Entrapped air normally exists in the form of relatively __________ air voids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Absent",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemically inactive pore fillers improve the workability and to facilitate the reduction of water for given workability and to make dense concrete which is basically impervious."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "What are plasticizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Which adds water for workability",
            "b) Which reduces water for workability",
            "c) Which decreases workability at the same water content",
            "d) Which oxidizes water for workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The organic substances or combinations of organic and inorganic substances, which allow a reduction in water content for the given workability, or give higher workability at the same water content."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Which one is an anionic surfactants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyglycol esters",
            "b) Hydroxylated carboxylic acids",
            "c) Lignosulphonates",
            "d) Carbohydrates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anionic surfactants such as lignosulphonates and their modifications and derivatives, salts of sulphonates hydrocarbons."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "What is the amount used of plasticizers in cement by weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) .1-.4%",
            "c) 1%",
            "d) 1-2%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plasticizers are used in the amount of 0.1 percentage to 0.4 percentage by weight of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What is the limitation of plasticizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A good plasticizer is one which does not cause air-entrainment in concrete > .1-.2%",
            "b) A good plasticizer is one which does not cause air-entrainment in concrete > 5%",
            "c) A good plasticizer is one which does not cause air-entrainment in concrete > 10-20%",
            "d) A good plasticizer is one which does not cause air-entrainment in concrete > 1-2%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A good plasticizer is one which does not cause air-entrainment in concrete is greater than 1-2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "At constant workability, what is the reduction in mixing water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) .1-.4%",
            "d) 5-15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: At constant workability, the reduction in mixing water is expected to be of the order of 5% to 15%."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Where do we use plasticizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Where low degree of workability is required",
            "b) Where medium degree of workability is required",
            "c) Where high degree of workability is required",
            "d) Where very low degree of workability is required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Where low degree of workability is required like Deep beams, column and beam junctions."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "What is super plasticizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Which adds water for workability",
            "b) Which reduces high range of water for workability",
            "c) Which decreases workability at the same water content",
            "d) Which oxidizes water for workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The organic substances or combinations of organic and inorganic substances, which allow a high reduction in water content for the given workability at the same water content."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "What is the allowed reduction of water with super plasticizers without reducing workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 30%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Super plasticizers permits reduction of water content about 30% without reducing the workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "What is the limitation of Carboxylic acids in High range water reducers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) .1%",
            "c) .2%",
            "d) .3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is possible to use w/c ratio as low as 0.25 or even lower and yet to make flowing concrete to obtain strength of order 120Mpa or more."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "What is accelerator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Which speed up the initial set of concrete",
            "b) Which delays the initial set of concrete",
            "c) Which speed up the final set of concrete",
            "d) Which delays the final set of concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An admixture used to speed up the initial set of concrete is called accelerator."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "What is retender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Which speed up the initial set of concrete",
            "b) Which delays the initial set of concrete",
            "c) Which speed up the final set of concrete",
            "d) Which delays the final set of concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An admixture used to delay the initial set of concrete is called retender."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Retarders are used to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Offset the accelerating effect of cold weather on the setting of concrete",
            "b) Offset the accelerating effect of hot weather on the setting of concrete",
            "c) Offset the Retarding effect of cold weather on the setting of concrete",
            "d) Offset the Retarding effect of hot weather on the setting of concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NaOH speed up the initial rate of hydration of cement and also speed up the initial set of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "At normal temperatures addition of sugar _____________ per cent have little effect on the rate of hydration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5-1",
            "b) 1-2",
            "c) .05-.1",
            "d) .1-.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zinc delays the initial rate of hydration of cement and also delays the initial set of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium fluosilicates act as a retarders",
            "b) CaCl2 acts as a retarders",
            "c) Gypsum acts as a retarders",
            "d) Gypsum acts as an accelerators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Retarders are used to offset the accelerating effect of hot weather on the setting of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Setting time of cement increases by adding ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gypsum",
            "b) CaCl2",
            "c) NaOH",
            "d) Hydrogen peroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At normal temperatures addition of sugar .05-.1% have little effect on the rate of hydration, but if the quantity is increased to 0.2 percent, hydration can be retarded to such an extent that final set may not take place for 72 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Retarders used at grouting oil wells, where temperature is about _____________ oC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 150",
            "c) 200",
            "d) 250"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gypsum is well known retarders helps to accelerating effect of high temperature on setting properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Minute spherical bubbles of size ranging from ______________ microns.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-100",
            "b) 5-80",
            "c) 15-20",
            "d) 50-60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gypsum is often added to cement and concrete to slow down the drying time. Cement dries quickly. If not added, the cement will set immediately after mixing of water leaving no time for concrete placing."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "What is Silica Fume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica fume is a byproduct of producing silicon metal or ferrosilicon alloys",
            "b) Silica fume is a mono product of producing silicon metal or ferrosilicon alloys",
            "c) Most commonly found in nature as quartz and in various living organisms",
            "d) Hydrocarbon combustion affords the two principal carbon oxides: carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silica fume is a byproduct of producing silicon metal or ferrosilicon alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Silica fume is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less reactive",
            "b) Neutral",
            "c) More reactive",
            "d) Absent in concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the most beneficial uses for silica fume is in concrete, because of its both properties, it is a very reactive pozzolana."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Concrete containing silica fume can have very __________ strength and can be very __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, Durable",
            "b) High, Durable",
            "c) Low, brittle",
            "d) High, brittle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concrete containing silica fume can have very high strength and can be very durable."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Content of SiO2 in silica fume is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 52%",
            "b) 35%",
            "c) 21.9%",
            "d) 85-97%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The content of SiO2 in silica fume is 85-97%. 35% is the content of SiO2 in Calcareous (ASTM C618 Class C) Fly Ash. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Content of CaO in silica fume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 21",
            "c) 40",
            "d) <1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The content of CaO in silica fume is less than 1. 21 is the content of CaO in Calcareous (ASTM C618 Class C) Fly Ash."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The specific surface (m2/kg) of silica fume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 370",
            "b) 15000-30000",
            "c) 45000",
            "d) 420"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific surface area of silica fume can be measured with the BET method or nitrogen adsorption method. It typically ranges from 15,000 to 30,000 m2/kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Specific Gravity of silica fume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.38",
            "b) 2.65",
            "c) 2.94",
            "d) 2.22"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The specific gravity of silica fume is generally in the range of 2.2 to 2.3."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Bulk density of the silica fume varies from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 130-600 kg/m3",
            "b) 650 kg/mm3",
            "c) 75-150 kg/mm3",
            "d) 750 kg/mm3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bulk density of silica fume depends on the degree of densification in the silo and varies from 130 (undensified) to 600 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Spherical particles in silica fume has diameter of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) <1 μm",
            "b) >1 μm",
            "c) 1 μm",
            "d) .1 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silica fume is an ultrafine material with spherical particles less than 1 μm in diameter, the average being about 0.15 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Silica fume is usually added during ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before concrete production at a concrete plant",
            "b) After concrete production at a concrete plant",
            "c) Concrete production at a concrete plant",
            "d) Curing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silica fume for use in concrete is available in wet or dry forms. It is usually added during concrete production at a concrete plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What is the content of SiO2 in fly ash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-60%",
            "b) 15-30%",
            "c) Up to 30%",
            "d) 1-7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The content of SiO2 in fly ash has been tested according to procedures specified in IS: 1727-1967."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "What is the content of Al2O3 in fly ash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-60%",
            "b) 15-30%",
            "c) Up to 30%",
            "d) 1-7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The content of Al2O3 in fly ash has been tested according to procedures specified in IS: 1727-1967."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "What is the content of unburnt fuel in fly ash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-60%",
            "b) 15-30%",
            "c) Up to 30%",
            "d) 1-7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The content of unburnt fuel in fly ash has been tested according to procedures specified in IS: 1727-1967."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Air entrainment in concrete increases ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Workability",
            "c) The effect of temp variations",
            "d) The unit weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are the following types of Air entrainment in concrete which helps to increase the workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Find the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clay and shales",
            "b) Opalinccherts",
            "c) Diatomaceous earth",
            "d) Surkhi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Clay and shales, opalinccherts, diatomaceous earth are natural pozzolnanas and surkhi is artificial one."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Find the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fly ash",
            "b) Silica Fume",
            "c) Rice husk ash",
            "d) Volcanic tuffs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fly ash, silica fume, rice husk ash are artificial pozzolnanas and Volcanic tuffs are the natural one."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Find the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finely divided minerals",
            "b) Air entraining agents",
            "c) Synthetic derivatives",
            "d) Natural derivatives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Finely divided minerals, Air entraining agents, Synthetic derivatives are the types of plasticizers."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Find the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water reducing plasticizers",
            "b) Water reducing plasticizers",
            "c) High performance plasticizers",
            "d) Super plasticizers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water reducing plasticizers, Water reducing plasticizers, High performance plasticizers are the types of plasticizers available in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which one is not chemical admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accelerators",
            "b) Retarders",
            "c) Water-reducing agents",
            "d) Silica fume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Accelerators, retarders, water reducing agents are the chemical admixtures and silica fumes is mineral admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which one is not part of chemical and mineral admixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curing compounds",
            "b) GGBFS",
            "c) Metakaoline",
            "d) Pumicites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GGBFS and Metakaoline are mineral admixtures and Pumicites is the artificial admixtures."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Air entrainment in concrete increases ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Workability",
            "c) The effect of temp variations",
            "d) The unit weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are following types of Air entrainment in concrete which helps to increase the workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "In a dry environment, concrete strength will be loosed as much as ___________ % in moist environment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Laboratory tests show that concrete strength will be loosed as much as 50% in dry environment as compared to moist environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Concrete placed in cold weather will take ____________ time to gain strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) No",
            "b) Less",
            "c) More",
            "d) Equal to hot weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete placed in cold weather will take longer time to gain strength, delaying form removal and subsequent construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "After finishing concrete surface must be kept ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry",
            "b) First dry it and then wet it",
            "c) First wet it and then dry it",
            "d) Wet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After finishing concrete surface must be kept wet, so that it’d be prevented from evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Dry intervals in surface wetting leads to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cracking",
            "b) Fogging",
            "c) High strength",
            "d) Good workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry intervals or patches can lead to crazing or cracking on the slab surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Damp proofing ____________ resist water well enough.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Does",
            "b) Does not",
            "c) Doesn’t effect",
            "d) Depends on the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Damp proofing does not resist water well enough to prevent oversaturation from ground water, or excessive and constant humidity."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Chemically active pore fillers ____________ the setting of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retards",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Accelerates",
            "d) No change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemically active pore fillers accelerates the setting of concrete and thus render the concrete more impervious at an early age."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Chemically inactive pore fillers ____________ the workability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Don’t affect",
            "d) Improve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemically inactive pore fillers improve the workability and to facilitate the reduction of water for given workability and to make dense concrete which is basically impervious."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "What do you mean by workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ASTM C 125 defines workability as the property determining the effort required to manipulate a freshly mixed quantity of concrete with a maximum loss of homogeneity",
            "b) ASTM C 125 defines workability as the property determining the effort required to manipulate a freshly mixed quantity of concrete with minimum loss of heterogeneity",
            "c) The strict definition of workability is the amount of useful external work, against the external friction between the individual particles in the concrete, necessary to produce full compaction",
            "d) The workability is also defined as the ease with which a freshly mixed concrete can be properly compacted and also that it can be transported, placed, and finished"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The workability is defined as the ease with which a freshly mixed concrete can be properly compacted and also that it can be transported, placed, and finished."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete can be improved by the addition of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron",
            "b) Sodium",
            "c) Zinc",
            "d) Sulphur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inorganic retardants include oxides of lead, zinc, phosphate and magnesium salts. Most retarders also act as water reducers."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete can be improved by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More sand",
            "b) More cement",
            "c) More fine aggregates",
            "d) Fineness of coarse aggregate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Workability of concrete can be improved by more cement and water with proper water cement ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete can be improved by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing size of aggregates",
            "b) Decreasing size of aggregates",
            "c) Increasing fine aggregates",
            "d) Increasing flaky aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Workability should be obtained by the use of a well-graded aggregate which has the largest maximum particle size possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete is directly proportional to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grading of the aggregates",
            "b) Time of transit",
            "c) Aggregates cement ratio",
            "d) Water cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grading of aggregate: Poor grading reduces consistency. That’s why it is directly proportional to grading of the aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete is inversely proportional to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grading of the aggregates",
            "b) Time of transit",
            "c) Aggregates cement ratio",
            "d) Water cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Workability of concrete is inversely proportional to the Water cement ratio because if the amount of w/c ratio increases, workability decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "If compaction factor of concrete is .90, then workability is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Very low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At the less workable end of this group, manually compacted flat slabs using crushed aggregates. Normal reinforced concrete manually compacted and heavily reinforced sections with vibration."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "A compaction factor of .85 for a cement concrete sample indicates ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low workability",
            "b) Medium workability",
            "c) Good workability",
            "d) Very good workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Roads vibrated by hand-operated machines. At the more workable end of this group, concrete may be manually compacted in roads using aggregate of rounded or irregular shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Adding water increases __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Workability",
            "b) Strength",
            "c) Fame",
            "d) Quality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adding water increases workability because it is inversely proportional to the workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Why Shape and texture of aggregates is a must?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth surfaces give better workability",
            "b) Smooth surfaces give poor workability",
            "c) Rough surfaces give better workability",
            "d) Rough surfaces give poor workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of smooth and rounded, rather than irregularly shaped aggregate also increases workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "How many types of tests are there to find workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 5 types of test to find the workability of a concrete i.e. slump test, compacting factor test, flow table test, vebe test, Kelly ball test."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "These test find workability __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly",
            "b) Indirectly",
            "c) 0",
            "d) Equals to the weight of the cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unfortunately, there are no accepted tests, which can measure directly the workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Workability of concrete is measured by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vicat apparatus test",
            "b) Slump test",
            "c) Minimum void method",
            "d) Talbot Richard test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Work ability of concrete is measured by slump cone test, compaction factor test. Slump cone is used for medium work ability. For high work abilities it is not accurate.Slump values vary from 0 mm to 300 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which test gives good results for rich mixes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump test",
            "b) Compacting factor test",
            "c) Flow table test",
            "d) VeBe test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a test used extensively in site work all over the world. Very useful in detecting variations in the uniformity of a mix of given nominal proportions."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which test used for low workable concretes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump test",
            "b) Compacting factor test",
            "c) Flow table test",
            "d) VeBe test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The degree of compaction, called compacting factor, is measured by the density ratio, i.e. the ratio of the density of actually achieved in the test to the density of the same concrete fully compacted."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which test Used for high workable concretes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump test",
            "b) Compacting factor test",
            "c) Flow table test",
            "d) VeBe test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compacting factor test used for high workable concretes. It measures the diameter of spread after vibration."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which test used for fiber reinforced concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump test",
            "b) Compacting factor test",
            "c) Flow table test",
            "d) VeBe test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Start time after removing cone and stop counter once the transparent rider is covered with paste. Record in seconds. This is VeBe time."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "___________ is practical in field test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump test",
            "b) Compacting factor test",
            "c) Flow table test",
            "d) Kelly Ball Test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It measures the depth of penetration. Kelly Ball Test is practical in field test."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "What is the compaction factor for medium degree of workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .78",
            "b) .85",
            "c) .92",
            "d) .95"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The compaction factor for medium degree of workability is .92 and .78 is the compaction for a very low degree."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "What is the Vee-Bee time for medium degree of workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-20 sec",
            "b) 5-10 sec",
            "c) 2-5 sec",
            "d) 35 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 2-5 sec is the Vee-Bee time for the medium degree of workability and 10-20 sec is for very low."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The water–cement ratio is the ratio of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of water to the weight of cement",
            "b) Volume of water to the volume of cement",
            "c) Density of water to the Density of cement",
            "d) Weight of water to the weight of aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water–cement ratio is the ratio of the weight of water to the weight of cement used in a concrete mix."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "A lower ratio leads to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher strength and durability",
            "b) Higher strength but low durability",
            "c) Lower strength but high durability",
            "d) Lower strength and durability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A lower ratio leads to higher strength and durability, but may make the mix difficult to work with and form."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Workability can be resolved __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) With not using of plasticizers",
            "b) With use of plasticizers",
            "c) With the use of both plasticizers and super plasticizers",
            "d) With not using of both plasticizers and super plasticizers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasticizers and super plasticizers helps to improve the workability to construct the building."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "How to improve the workability of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the w/c ratio",
            "b) Decrease the w/c ratio",
            "c) Decrease the size of aggregates",
            "d) Don’t mix it for longer time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is clear vision from the image that the amount of water is more as compared to cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "What is workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When it is easily placed and compacted heterogeneous",
            "b) When it is easily placed and compacted homogenous",
            "c) When it is not easily placed",
            "d) When it is easily placed but not compacted homogenous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option A figure has low porosity because the content of water is less as compared to cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "What is the compaction factor for low degree of workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .78",
            "b) .85",
            "c) .92",
            "d) .95"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increasing the water cement ratio, helps in improving the workability of the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "What is the moisture content in slurry for wet process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35-50%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 40-45%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moisture content in slurry for wet process is 35-50%. 12% is the moisture content for dry process."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The slurry, in its movement down the kiln, encounters a progressively higher temperature. At first, the water is driven off and __________ is liberated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SiO2",
            "b) CO2",
            "c) Gypsum",
            "d) CaO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At 900°C limestone decomposes, CaCO3.CaO + CO2 (endothermic reaction) CO2 is swept away by current air."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "For complete hydration of cement the w/c ratio needed is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than 0.25",
            "b) More than 0.25 but less than 0.35",
            "c) More than 0.35 but less than 0.60",
            "d) More than 0.60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A mix with a ratio of 0.45 may not mix thoroughly, and may not flow well enough to be placed. More water is therefore used than is technically necessary to react with cement. Water–cement ratios of 0.45 to 0.60 are more typically used."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "The minimum water to cement ratio for cement concrete to hydrate is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.38",
            "d) 0.27"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum water cement ratio is 0.38. It cannot be 35 kg. W/C ratio depends on the exposure condition of concrete but minimum water cement ratio is 0.38 for full hydration of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Approximate percentage range of A2O3 in OPC is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17-25",
            "b) 3-8",
            "c) 3- 10",
            "d) 4-15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Percentage of A2O3 is 3-8, CaO has 60-67, SiO2 has 17-25, SO3 is 1-3, MgO has .1-4 and soda has .5-1.3."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of iron oxide in white cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Very high",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As iron oxide gives the grey colour to cement, it is therefore necessary for white cement to keep the content of iron oxide as low as possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of air by volume in Air Entraining Cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-4",
            "b) 10-11",
            "c) 7-8",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Entertainment of air also improves work ability and durability. It is recommended that air contents should be 03-04 % by volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "What is curing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dehydration",
            "b) Hydration",
            "c) Drying",
            "d) Dipping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curing refers to hydration, the chemical process by which concrete hardens once it is poured."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "In a dry environment, concrete strength will be loosed as much as _________ % in the moist environment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Laboratory tests show that concrete strength will be loosed as much as 50% in dry environment as compared to moist environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Concrete placed in cold weather will take __________ time to gain strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) No",
            "b) Less",
            "c) More",
            "d) Equal to hot weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete placed in cold weather will take longer time to gain strength, delaying form removal and subsequent construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "After finishing concrete surface must be kept _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry",
            "b) First dry it and then wet it",
            "c) First wet it and then dry it",
            "d) Wet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After finishing concrete surface must be kept wet, so that it’d be prevented from evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Dry intervals in surface wetting leads to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cracking",
            "b) Fogging",
            "c) High strength",
            "d) Good workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry intervals or patches can lead to crazing or cracking on the slab surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Contractors place blankets over the concrete to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the rate of evaporation",
            "b) Slow the rate of evaporation",
            "c) To increase the strength",
            "d) Ease to do work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A more common practice is for contractors to place blankets over the slab surface to slow the rate of evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Well cured concrete _________ thermal, plastic & drying shrinkage cracks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doesn’t affect",
            "b) Maximize",
            "c) Minimize",
            "d) Create"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Well cured concrete can minimize thermal, plastic & drying shrinkage cracks, making concrete more water tight, thus preventing moisture and water borne chemicals from entering into the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which method is the most common and cheaper for water curing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ponding",
            "b) Sprinkling",
            "c) Mist curing",
            "d) Wet covering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ponding is the most common and inexpensive method of curing flat surfaces such as floor slabs, flat roofs, pavements and other horizontal surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The hydration that provides the initial mix and chemical bond of the concrete’s ingredients is the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) First step",
            "b) Second step",
            "c) Third step",
            "d) Fourth step"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydration that provides the initial mix and chemical bond of the concrete’s ingredients is the first step, but in order for the slab to be properly prepared for its final finish or flooring."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the full form of rH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhesus factor",
            "b) Relative humidity",
            "c) Rush hour",
            "d) Radio head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Relative Humidity (RH) is the ratio of the amount of water vapor in the air at a specific temperature to the maximum amount that the air could hold at that temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Water cement ratio is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume of water to the volume of cement",
            "b) Volume of water to the volume of concrete",
            "c) Volume of concrete to the volume of cement",
            "d) Volume of water to the volume of aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water–cement ratio is the ratio of the weight of water to the weight of cement used in a concrete mix."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "A lower ratio leads to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) High strength",
            "b) Low strength",
            "c) Low durability",
            "d) Ease to work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A lower ratio leads to higher strength and durability, but may make the mix difficult to work with and form."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "For concrete exposed to a very aggressive environment the w/c should be lower than _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) .5",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Higher is the aggressiveness of the environment lower should be the w/c ratio. For concrete exposed to a very aggressive environment, the w/c should be lower than 0.40."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "What is the range of water in M10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34-36L",
            "b) 29-32L",
            "c) 26-30L",
            "d) 21-27L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of water for M10 (1:3:6) is 34 to 36 liters with a weight of 226kg of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "What is the range of water in M15?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34-36L",
            "b) 29-32L",
            "c) 26-30L",
            "d) 21-27L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of water for M15 (1:2:4) is 29 to 32 liters with a weight of 313kg of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is the range of water in M20?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34-36L",
            "b) 29-32L",
            "c) 26-30L",
            "d) 21-27L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The range of water for M20 (1:1.5:3) is 26 to 30 liters with a weight of 404kg of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "What is the range of water in M25?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34-36L",
            "b) 29-32L",
            "c) 26-30L",
            "d) 21-27L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The range of water for M25 (1:1:2) is 21 to 27 liters with a weight of 563 kg of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "What is the approximate quantity of water in M5?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60L",
            "b) 45L",
            "c) 34L",
            "d) 85L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The approximate quantity of water in grade M5 is nearly equal to 60 liters."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is the approximate quantity of water in M7?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60L",
            "b) 45L",
            "c) 34L",
            "d) 85L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The approximate quantity of water in grade M7 is nearly equal to 45 liters."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "What is the approximate quantity of water in M10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60L",
            "b) 45L",
            "c) 34L",
            "d) 85L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The approximate quantity of water in grade M10 is nearly equal to 34 liters."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "What is the gel/space ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume of water to the volume of cement",
            "b) Volume of the hydrated cement paste to the sum of volumes of the hydrated cement",
            "c) Volume of the hydrated cement paste to the sum of volumes of the hydrated cement and of the capillary pores",
            "d) Volume of gel to the volume of space present in the concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This ratio is defined as the ratio of the volume of the hydrated cement paste to the sum of volumes of the hydrated cement and of the capillary pores."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Who has established the relation between the strength and gel/space ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrams",
            "b) Power",
            "c) Brownyard",
            "d) Power and Brownyard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Powers and Brownyard have established the relationship between the strength and gel/space ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Power showed that the strength of concrete bears a specific relationship with the gel/space ratio. He found the relationship to be  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 240x3",
            "b) 140x3",
            "c) 240x2",
            "d) 140x2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power’s experiment showed that the strength of concrete bears a specific relationship with the gel/space ratio. He found the relationship to be 240 x3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What does 240 in power’s experiment stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gel space ratio",
            "b) Water cement ratio",
            "c) Intrinsic strength of gel",
            "d) Extrinsic strength of gel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power’s experiment showed that the strength of concrete bears a specific relationship with the gel/space ratio and the relationship comes to be 240 x 3 where 240 represents the intrinsic strength of the gel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "What does x3 in power’s experiment stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gel space ratio",
            "b) Water cement ratio",
            "c) Intrinsic strength of gel",
            "d) Extrinsic strength of gel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Power found the relationship to be 240 x3, where the value of x is the gel/space."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What unit is present with the 240?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pa",
            "b) MPa",
            "c) GPa",
            "d) KPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During Power’s experiment, the intrinsic strength of the gel was comes out to be 240MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Gel/Space ratio = x = Volume of gel / Space available = 0.657 C / 0.319 C+ Wo. Here C stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of cement in kg",
            "b) Weight of cement in g",
            "c) Volume of gel",
            "d) Volume of mixing water in ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Power and his experiment, the C is the weight of cement in grams. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Gel/Space ratio = x = Volume of gel / Space available = 0.657 C / 0.319 C+ Wo. Here Wo stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight of cement in kg",
            "b) Weight of cement in g",
            "c) Volume of gel",
            "d) Volume of mixing water in ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Power and his experiment, Wo is the volume of mixing water in ml."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What is concrete maturity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concrete strength is directly related to age history",
            "b) Concrete strength is indirectly related to age history",
            "c) Concrete strength is directly related to age and its temperature history",
            "d) Concrete strength is indirectly related to age and its temperature history"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maturity concept uses the principle that concrete strength is indirectly related to age and its temperature history."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Maturity methods provide a ___________ simple approach for strength of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relatively",
            "b) Technically",
            "c) Absolutely",
            "d) Actually"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maturity method provide a relatively simple approach for reliably estimating the in-place early age compressive strength of concrete during construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "The maturity method is a ___________ approach to predict the early age strength gain of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difficult",
            "b) Convenient",
            "c) Inconvenient",
            "d) There is no such method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maturity method is a convenient approach to predict the early age strength gain of concrete, using the principle that the concrete strength is directly related to the hydration temperature history of cementitious paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "It is a __________ method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Destructive Testing",
            "b) Nondestructive testing",
            "c) Ring Tension Test",
            "d) Compression Test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a non-destructive testing method as contrasted to breaking cylinders in the laboratory."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "It __________ the quantity and ___________ cost of sampling and testing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases, Increases",
            "b) Decreases, decreases",
            "c) Increases, Decreases",
            "d) Decreases, Increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It reduces the quantity and cost of sampling and testing by reducing the number of cylinders that need to be cast and broken to determine strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "A lower ratio leads to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High strength",
            "b) Low strength",
            "c) Low durability",
            "d) Ease to work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A lower ratio leads to higher strength and durability, but may make the mix difficult to work with and form."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The material used for UHPC provides compressive strengths up to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17000 psi",
            "b) 20000 psi",
            "c) 25000 psi",
            "d) 29000 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The material provides compressive strengths up to 29000 pounds per square inch."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "What could be the possible answer among the following for compressive strength of high strength concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10MPa",
            "b) 20MPa",
            "c) 30MPa",
            "d) 40MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High strength of concrete has the compressive strength greater or equal to 40MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "What could be the possible answer among the following for water cement ratio for high strength concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5",
            "b) .45",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High strength of concrete made by lowering the water cement ratio nearly equal to 0.35 or less."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Due to low w/c ratio ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It doesn’t cause any problems",
            "b) It causes problems",
            "c) Workability is easy",
            "d) Strength is more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to low water cement ratio, it causes problems so superplasticizers are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which type of aggregates are used to produce 70MPa compressive strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All in one",
            "b) Fine",
            "c) Coarse",
            "d) Flaky"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To produce 70 MPa compressive strength, coarse aggregates are being used in HSC."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates are used to produce 70MPa compressive strength is  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20-30 mm",
            "b) 10-20 mm",
            "c) 30-40 mm",
            "d) 40-50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates is 20-30 mm are used to produce 70MPa compressive strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates are used to produce 100MPa compressive strength is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20-30 mm",
            "b) 10-20 mm",
            "c) 30-40 mm",
            "d) 40-50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates is 10-20 mm are used to produce 100MPa compressive strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Use of HSC in column __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It increase the size of the column",
            "b) It decrease the size of the column",
            "c) Doesn’t affect",
            "d) Decrease the strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In bridges, HSC is being used to reduce the number of beams for supporting span."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Use of HSC in column ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the no of steel required in the same column",
            "b) Increase the no of steel required in the same column",
            "c) Decrease the no of steel required in the different column",
            "d) Increase the no of steel required in the different column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Use of HSC in the column section decreases the size of the column and used in high rise buildings."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "High strength concrete is defined purely on the basis __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compressive strength",
            "b) Poor strength",
            "c) Tensile strength",
            "d) Good strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Use of HSC in a column, decrease the number of steel required in the same column."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Ultra-High Performance Concrete (UHPC), also known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active powder concrete",
            "b) NPC",
            "c) Reactive powder concrete",
            "d) High Strength concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ultra-High Performance Concrete (UHPC), also known as reactive powder concrete (RPC), is a high-strength, ductile material."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The material used for UHPC provides compressive strengths up to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17000 psi",
            "b) 20000 psi",
            "c) 25000 psi",
            "d) 29000 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The material provides compressive strengths of up to 29000 pounds per square inch."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The material used for UHPC provides flexural strengths up to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000 psi",
            "b) 5000 psi",
            "c) 7000 psi",
            "d) 10000 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The material used for UHPC provides flexural strengths up to 7000 pounds per square inch."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Range of modulus of elasticity for UHPC ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-35 GPa",
            "b) 35-40 GPa",
            "c) 40-45 GPa",
            "d) 45-50 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 45-50 GPa or 6500 to 7300 ksi is the range of modulus of elasticity for ultra-high performance concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "What is the compressive strength for UHPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-20 MPa",
            "b) 60-100 MPa",
            "c) 100-150 MPa",
            "d) >150 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 28 days compressive strength for UHPC is 100-150MPa and for HPC, it’s 60-100 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of water by weight in UHPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.5",
            "b) 4.4",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 6.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 4.4 is the percentage of water by weight in UHPC according to the typical composition of Ductal."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of PC by weight in UHPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.5",
            "b) 4.4",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 6.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 28.5 is the percentage of PC by weight in UHPC according to the typical composition of Ductal."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of steel fibre by weight in UHPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.5",
            "b) 4.4",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 6.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 6.5 is the percentage of steel fibre by weight in UHPC according to the typical composition of Ductal."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of the accelerator by weight in UHPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.5",
            "b) 4.4",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 6.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 1.2 is the percentage of the accelerator by weight in UHPC according to typical composition of Ductal."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "It is ___________ strength and ___________ permeability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High, high",
            "b) Low, low",
            "c) High, low",
            "d) Low, high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is specifically chosen so as to have particularly appropriate properties for the expected use of the structure such as high strength and low permeability."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Concrete having 28- days’ compressive strength in the range of 60 to 100 MPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) HPC",
            "b) VHPC",
            "c) OPC",
            "d) HSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High Performance concrete works out to be economical, even though its initial cost is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Concrete having 28-days compressive strength in the range of 100 to 150 MPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) HPC",
            "b) VHPC",
            "c) OPC",
            "d) HSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Major applications of high-performance concrete in the field of Civil Engineering constructions have been in the areas of long-span bridges, high-rise buildings or structures, highway pavements, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "High-Performance Concrete is ____________ as compared to Normal Strength Concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less brittle",
            "b) Brittle",
            "c) More brittle",
            "d) Highly ductile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High Performance Concrete having 28- days’ compressive strength in the range of 60 to 100 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The choice of cement for high-strength concrete should not be based only on mortar-cube tests but it should also include tests of compressive strengths of concrete at ___________ days.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28, 56, 91",
            "b) 28, 60, 90",
            "c) 30, 60, 90",
            "d) 30, 45, 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Very high performing Concrete having 28-days compressive strength in the range of 100 to 150 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "For high-strength concrete, a cement should produce a minimum 7-days mortar-cube strength of approximately ___ MPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High-Performance Concrete is more brittle as compared to Normal Strength Concrete (NSC), especially when high strength is the main criteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "____________ mm nominal maximum size aggregates gives optimum strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.5 and 10.5",
            "b) 10.5 and 12.5",
            "c) 9.5 and 12.5",
            "d) 11.5 and 12.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The choice of cement for high-strength concrete should not be based only on mortar-cube tests but it should also include tests of compressive strengths of concrete at 28, 56, and 91 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Due to low w/c ratio _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It doesn’t cause any problems",
            "b) It causes problems",
            "c) Workability is easy",
            "d) Strength is more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For high-strength concrete, a cement should produce a minimum 7-days mortar-cube strength of approximately 30 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Clay minerals are found in most _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous Environment",
            "b) Sedimentary environment",
            "c) Metamorphic environment",
            "d) In all environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clay minerals are common in sedimentary formations and seismic measurements are our main tools for studying sub-surface lithology."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Theoretical value for bulk modulus of clay __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 and 50 GPa",
            "b) 30 and 40 GPa",
            "c) 100-150 GPa",
            "d) 200 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Theoretical value for bulk modulus of clay are reported between 20 and 50 GPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Young’s modulus for dickite is  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.2 GPa",
            "b) 6.2 GPa",
            "c) 7.2 GPa",
            "d) 8.2 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Young’s modulus on clay particles using atomic force acoustic microscopy is measured for dickite is 6.2 GPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "The grain density of the clay powders was measured using _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrostatic pressure",
            "b) Cylindrical cavity",
            "c) Pycnometer",
            "d) Helium porosimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The grain density of the clay powders was measured using a pycnometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "To avoid trapped air produced by clay flocculation, we used ___ in distilled water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) (NaPO3)6",
            "b) Na4P2O7",
            "c) Na5P3O10",
            "d) PO4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To avoid trapped air produced by clay flocculation, we used sodium hexametaphosphate in distilled water."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "For the cold-pressed aggregate samples, porosity, bulk and grain densities were measured with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrostatic pressure",
            "b) Cylindrical cavity",
            "c) Pycnometer",
            "d) Helium porosimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For the cold-pressed aggregate samples, porosity, bulk and grain densities were measured at room P–T conditions with a helium porosimeter."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "IS 456 of 2000 gives the modulus of elasticity as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ec = 5000 fck.5",
            "b) Ec = 5000 fck2",
            "c) Ec = 5000 fck3",
            "d) Ec = 5000 fck1/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 456 of 2000 gives the modulus of elasticity as Ec = 5000 fck.5 where Ec is the modulus of elasticity in N/mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "What are elastic strains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are the instantaneous deformations that occur when an external stress is first applied",
            "b) These deformations occur either on loss of moisture from the concrete on cooling of concrete",
            "c) It is the time-dependent deformation that occurs on the prolonged application of stress",
            "d) Any one or combinations of the above types of deformations in a hardened concrete leads to cracking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Elastic strain in concrete, as defined above, depends on the externally applied stress and the modulus of elasticity of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Static modulus of elasticity of concrete has been related to its ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile strength",
            "b) Compressive strength",
            "c) External strength",
            "d) Applied force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Static modulus of elasticity of concrete has been related to its compressive strength by the various Standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "If the value of fck is 100 then what will be the modulus of elasticity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5000",
            "b) 500",
            "c) 50000",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modulus of elasticity as Ec = 5000 fck.5 =000*100.5 =5000*10 =  =50000."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Creep is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time dependent",
            "b) Time independent",
            "c) Pressure dependent",
            "d) Temperature dependent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the time-dependent deformation that occurs on the prolonged application of stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "If the creep effect is considered at a given load, the modulus determined is referred to as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short term modulus of elasticity",
            "b) Elasticity",
            "c) Long term modulus of elasticity",
            "d) Creep effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If creep effect is considered at a given load, the modulus determined is referred to as long term modulus of elasticity."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "If θ is creep coefficient then what is Elong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eshort /(1+θ)",
            "b) Eshort *(1+θ)",
            "c) Eavg /(1+θ)",
            "d) Eavg *(1+θ)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eshort /(1+θ), Where θ is creep coefficient and Creep coefficient is the ratio of creep strain to elastic strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Concrete exhibits initial elastic strain which depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnitude of applied stress",
            "b) Rate of applied stress",
            "c) Magnitude and rate of applied stress",
            "d) Elastic modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete exhibits initial elastic strain which depends on the magnitude and rate of applied stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "This strain increases over time due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Creep",
            "b) Elastic modulus",
            "c) Short term modulus of elasticity",
            "d) Long term modulus of elasticity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This strain increases over time due to creep where the concrete will experience inelastic deformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "If the stress is removed, the specimen shows an instantaneous recovery strain ___ the elastic strain on loading.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher than",
            "b) Lower than",
            "c) Equal to",
            "d) Much greater than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the stress is removed, the specimen shows an instantaneous recovery strain lower than the elastic strain on loading, followed by gradual decrease in strain (creep recovery) over time."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "According to Lamond and Pielert, it’s the ____ that exhibits creep upon application of load on a concrete specimen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aggregates",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Cement paste",
            "d) Admixtures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Lamond and Pielert, it’s the cement paste that exhibits creep upon application of load on a concrete specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "When concrete is loaded it experiences a large strain upon loading known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differential elastic strain",
            "b) Instantaneous elastic strain",
            "c) Differential inelastic strain",
            "d) Instantaneous inelastic strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When concrete is loaded it experiences a large strain upon loading known as the instantaneous elastic strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Aggregate has therefore a direct effect on the long-term deformations of concrete because __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low elastic modulus aggregate will produce a stiffer concrete that will have relatively higher resistance to deformation",
            "b) High elastic modulus aggregate will produce a stiffer concrete that will have relatively higher resistance to deformation",
            "c) High elastic modulus aggregate will produce a stiffer concrete that will have relatively lower resistance to deformation",
            "d) Low elastic modulus aggregate will produce a stiffer concrete that will have relatively lower resistance to deformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aggregate has therefore a direct effect on the long-term deformations of concrete because a high elastic modulus aggregate will produce a stiffer concrete that will have relatively higher resistance to deformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Creep ___ as the age of application of load _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase, increase",
            "b) Increase, decrease",
            "c) Decrease, decrease",
            "d) Decrease, increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Creep decreases as the age of application of load increases, because of strength increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "The __________ the aggregate, the ________ is the magnitude of creep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stronger, more",
            "b) Weaker, more",
            "c) Stronger, less",
            "d) Weaker, less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stronger the aggregate the more is the restraining effect and hence the less is the magnitude of creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The _________ the modulus of elasticity the _________ is the creep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher, more",
            "b) Lower, more",
            "c) Higher, less",
            "d) Lower, less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It can be easily imagined that the higher the modulus of elasticity the less is the creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "A ________ paste structure undergoes ________ creep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good, high",
            "b) Poor, high",
            "c) Good, average",
            "d) Poor, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of paste content and its quality is one of the most important factors influencing creep. A poorer paste structure undergoes higher creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Creep is _________ to the strength of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Similar",
            "c) Directly proportional",
            "d) Inversely proportional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Creep increases with increase in water/cement ratio. In other words, it can also be said that creep is inversely proportional to the strength of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The rate of creep rapidly ________ with time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Doesn’t affect",
            "d) Depends on the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of creep rapidly decreases with time. The time taken by a concrete structure to attained creep is 5 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Aggregates with moisture movement and _________ elastic modulus cause a _________ amount of creep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High, higher",
            "b) Low, lower",
            "c) High, lower",
            "d) Low, higher"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aggregates with moisture movement and low elastic modulus cause a large amount of creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "The rate of creep generally _________ with the _________ of the size of aggregates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase, increase",
            "b) Decrease, decease",
            "c) Increase, decrease",
            "d) 2.5, 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rate of creep generally decreases with the increase of the size of aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Static modulus of elasticity of concrete has been related to its ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile strength",
            "b) Compressive strength",
            "c) External strength",
            "d) Applied force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Static modulus of elasticity of concrete has been related to its compressive strength by the various Standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Coefficient of thermal expansion of concrete is ________ coefficient of thermal expansion in aggregates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) More than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coefficient of thermal expansion of concrete increases with the increase in coefficient of thermal expansion of aggregates and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "How many types of shrinkages, caused due to loss of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shrinkage is the reduction in the volume of a fresh hardened concrete exposed to ambient temp and humidity."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "How many types of shrinkages, caused due to cooling and carbonation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 3 types of shrinkage that are caused due to loss of water i.e. plastic, drying and autogenous."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Reduction in the volume due to shrinkage causes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low volume",
            "b) Volumetric strain",
            "c) Volumetric stress",
            "d) W/c ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 2 types of shrinkage which are caused due to cooling and carbonation."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Volumetric strain is equal to ___________ times the linear strain.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reduction in the volume due to shrinkage causes volumetric strain in freshly hardened concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "In practice, shrinkage is measured simply as a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear strain",
            "b) Linear stress",
            "c) Volumetric strain",
            "d) Volumetric stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Volumetric strain is equal to 3 times the linear strain in freshly hardened concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "It is observed that 14-34% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 weeks",
            "b) 3 months",
            "c) 6 months",
            "d) 1 year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is observed that 14-34% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in 2 weeks."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "It is observed that 40-80% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 weeks",
            "b) 3 months",
            "c) 6 months",
            "d) 1 year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is observed that 40-80% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in 3 months."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "It is observed that 66-85% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 weeks",
            "b) 3 months",
            "c) 6 months",
            "d) 1 year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is observed that 66 to 85% of the 20 years shrinkage occurs in 1 year."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "The magnitude of autogenous shrinkage is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .001",
            "b) .0001",
            "c) .01",
            "d) .1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the concrete is placed in 100% relative humidity for a length of time then there won’t be any shrinkage instead there’ll be slight swelling."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which aggregates have high shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grave",
            "b) Sand stone",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Granite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnitude of autogenous shrinkage is in the order of about .0001."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which aggregates have low shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grave",
            "b) Sand stone",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Granite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aggregates plays an important role in the shrinkage properties of concrete. According to option, A is Sand stone."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "What is plastic shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not a result of any change in the concrete production process. Rather, it is a result of certain environmental conditions which occurs in the Central Missouri area",
            "b) It is defined as the contracting of a hardened concrete mixture due to the loss of capillary water. This shrinkage causes an increase in tensile",
            "c) It is an important phenomenon in young concrete. At low w/c ratios, less than about 0.42, all the water is rapidly drawn into the hydration process and the demand for more water creates very fine capillaries",
            "d) It occurs when the concrete is exposed to air containing carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is not a result of any change in the concrete production process. Rather, it is a result of certain environmental conditions which occurs in the Central Missouri area."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "What is drying shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not a result of any change in the concrete production process. Rather, it is a result of certain environmental conditions which frequently occur in the Central Missouri area",
            "b) It is defined as the contracting of a hardened concrete mixture due to the loss of capillary water. This shrinkage causes an increase in tensile",
            "c) It is an important phenomenon in young concrete. At low w/c ratios, less than about 0.42, all the water is rapidly drawn into the hydration process and the demand for more water creates very fine capillaries",
            "d) It occurs when the concrete is exposed to air containing carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is defined as the contracting of a hardened concrete mixture due to the loss of capillary water. This shrinkage causes an increase in tensile."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "What is autogenous shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not a result of any change in the concrete production process. Rather, it is a result of certain environmental conditions which frequently occur in the Central Missouri area",
            "b) It is defined as the contracting of a hardened concrete mixture due to the loss of capillary water. This shrinkage causes an increase in tensile",
            "c) It is an important phenomenon in young concrete. At low w/c ratios, less than about 0.42, all the water is rapidly drawn into the hydration process and the demand for more water creates very fine capillaries",
            "d) It occurs when the concrete is exposed to air containing carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is an important phenomenon in young concrete. At low w/c ratios, less than about 0.42, all the water is rapidly drawn into the hydration process and the demand for more water creates very fine capillaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "What is carbonation shrinkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not a result of any change in the concrete production process. Rather, it is a result of certain environmental conditions which frequently occur in the Central Missouri area",
            "b) It is defined as the contracting of a hardened concrete mixture due to the loss of capillary water. This shrinkage causes an increase in tensile",
            "c) It is an important phenomenon in young concrete. At low w/c ratios, less than about 0.42, all the water is rapidly drawn into the hydration process and the demand for more water creates very fine capillaries",
            "d) It occurs when the concrete is exposed to air containing carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It occurs when the concrete is exposed to air containing carbon dioxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "ACI 305.R.91 specifies Evaporation rate __ kg/hr/m2 should be avoided to prevent plastic cracking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) <.5",
            "b) =0.5",
            "c) >.5",
            "d) Not equal to .5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ACI 305.R.91 specifies Evaporation rate >0.5 kg/hr/m2 should be avoided to prevent plastic cracking."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Carbonic Acid + Ca(OH)2 ⇨ X. What is the main compound in X?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CaCO2",
            "b) CO2",
            "c) CaCO3",
            "d) H2O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is a chemical reaction. It causes contraction of concrete which is known as Carbonation shrinkage."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Reduction in the volume due to shrinkage causes _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low volume",
            "b) Volumetric strain",
            "c) Volumetric stress",
            "d) W/c ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If there is continuous supply of H2O to the concrete during hydration, concrete expands due to absorption of water by the cement gel and it is known as swelling."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Durability of concrete is proportional to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand content",
            "b) Water cement ratio",
            "c) Aggregate ratio",
            "d) Cement aggregate ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Volume chances due to difference in thermal properties of the aggregates and cement paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Strength of concrete show an increase with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease in rate of loading",
            "b) Increase in rate of loading",
            "c) Unaffected by rate of loading",
            "d) Depends on application of load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strength of concrete is directly proportional to the nature of the loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Strength of concrete is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(f_{ck} = K(\\frac{c}{C+W+A})^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(f_{ck} = K(\\frac{C+A}{C+W+A})^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(f_{ck} = K(\\frac{C+W}{C+W+A})^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(f_{ck} = K(\\frac{C+W+A}{C+W+A})^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the formula to find the Strength of concrete when we have the volume of cement, aggregates and water."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "As per & 5456:200 Young’s modulus of concrete is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 fck",
            "b) 5000 fck2",
            "c) 5700 fck",
            "d) 150 fck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 5000 fck2 is the formula of young’s modulus of the concrete according to IS 5456:200."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Strength of concrete is proportional to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand content",
            "b) Water cement ratio",
            "c) Aggregate ratio",
            "d) Cement water ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Strength of concrete is proportional to Cement water ratio and inversely proportional to w/c ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Strength of concrete increase with _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase with w/c ratio",
            "b) Decrease with w/c ratio",
            "c) Decrease in size of aggregates",
            "d) Decrease in curing time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As mentioned above that Strength of concrete is inversely proportional to w/c ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Strength of concrete increase with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase with w/c ratio",
            "b) Increase in fineness of cement",
            "c) Decrease in size of aggregates",
            "d) Decrease in curing time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strength of concrete increase with increase in fineness of the cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Approximate ratio of the strength of the cement conc of 7 days to that of 28 days (2/3)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .75",
            "b) .85",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 1.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After the lab broke the seven-day cylinders, the cylinder from the pier with added water broke at 1980 psi. The other seven-day cylinders were as high as 2620 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Approximate ratio of strength of the 30 cm cube to that of 15 cm cube is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.1",
            "b) 1",
            "c) .9",
            "d) .75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The strength of cylinder with diameter of 15cm and 30cm tall can be approximated as 0.84 of the strength of a 15x15x15 cm cube according to Eurocodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Approximate ratio of direct tensile strength to flexural strength is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .25",
            "b) .33",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .05"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Approximate ratio of direct tensile strength to flexural strength is .5 according to the formula."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "The addition of a pozzolanic admixture such as fly ash reduces the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) C3S",
            "b) C3A",
            "c) C2S",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The addition of a pozzolanic admixture such as fly ash reduces the C3A content of cement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Lowering of ____________ might also help, since this would reduce the amount of CH that forms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C3S",
            "b) C3A",
            "c) C2S",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lowering of C3S might also help, since this would reduce the amount of CH that forms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "When the ____________ content is low, most ettringite will be formed in the plastic state.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C3SS",
            "b) C3AA",
            "c) C2S",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the C3A content is low, most ettringite will be formed in the plastic state. "
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "The philosophy of prescribing low ____________ cement to improve resistance to sulphate attack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C3S",
            "b) C3A",
            "c) C2S",
            "d) C4AF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The philosophy of prescribing low C3A cement to improve resistance to sulphate attack hinges on the need to minimize ettringite formation after the concrete hardens. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "The quality of concrete, specifically a ____________ permeability, is the best protection against sulphate attack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quality of concrete, specifically a low permeability, is the best protection against sulphate attack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "For concrete exposed to a very aggressive environment the w/c should be lower than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) .5",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Higher is the aggressiveness of the environment lower should be the w/c ratio. For concrete exposed to a very aggressive environment, the w/c should be lower than 0.40. "
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The quality of concrete, specifically a ____________ w/c ratio, is the best protection against sulphate attack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quality of concrete, specifically a low w/c ratio, is the best protection against sulphate attack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The quality of concrete, specifically a ____________ cement content, is the best protection against sulphate attack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality of concrete, specifically a high cement content, is the best protection against sulphate attack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Concentration of water-soluble sulphates in water ___________ ppm for mild exposure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) <150",
            "b) 150-1500",
            "c) 150-10000",
            "d) >10000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Concentration of water-soluble sulphates in water less than 150 ppm for mild exposure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Concentration of water-soluble sulphates in water ___________ ppm for severe exposure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) <150",
            "b) 150-1500",
            "c) 150-10000",
            "d) >10000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concentration of water-soluble sulphates in water 150-10000 ppm for severe exposure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The breaking up of cohesion in a mass of concrete is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Workability",
            "b) Segregation",
            "c) Bleeding",
            "d) Creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Segregation in concrete is commonly thought as separation of some size groups of aggregates from cement mortar in isolated locations with corresponding deficiencies of these materials in other locations."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The continuous strain, which the concrete undergoes due to application of external loads, is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Workability",
            "b) Segregation",
            "c) Bleeding",
            "d) Creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The separation of water or water-cement mixture from the freshly mixed concrete is known as bleeding."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Harshness in concrete is due to the excess of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Finer particles",
            "c) Middle sized particle",
            "d) Coarser particle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The continuous strain, which the concrete undergoes due to application of external loads, is called creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Reinforced cement concrete is equally strong in taking __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile and compressive stresses",
            "b) Compressive and shear stresses",
            "c) Tensile, compressive and shear stresses",
            "d) Tensile and shear stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is the rough finishing property of concrete and causes improper proportioning, less compaction, low water content, excess of medium sized aggregates, deficiency of sand etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Plain cement concrete is strong in taking ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile stress",
            "b) Compressive stress",
            "c) Shear stress",
            "d) Tensile, compressive and shear stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to avoid segregation, the concrete should not be thrown from a height of 100 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "How many types of sulphates attack occur in concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IS 456:2000, Reinforced cement concrete is equally strong in taking Tensile, compressive and shear stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "What is internal sulphates attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphate are more usually are a result of high-sulphate soils",
            "b) Sulphate are more usually are a result of ground water",
            "c) Industrial waste water",
            "d) Hydraulic cements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plain cement concrete is strong in taking compressive stress and week in tensile stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is internal sulphates attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presence of natural gypsum in the aggregates",
            "b) Soil may contain excess of gypsum",
            "c) Sulphate are more usually are a result of ground water",
            "d) Industrial waste water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two types of sulphates attack in concrete and mortar i.e., internal attack and external attack."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "What is external sulphates attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Industrial waste water",
            "b) Presence of natural gypsum in the aggregates",
            "c) Hydraulic cements",
            "d) Portland cement might be over-sulphated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Internal sulphates attack are rarer but originates from such concrete-making materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Tensile test can be performed on _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact testing machine",
            "b) Universal testing machine",
            "c) Rockwell tester",
            "d) Brinell tester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tensile testing, also known as tension testing, is a fundamental material science test in which a sample is subjected to a controlled tension until failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which machine records the change in length of specimen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact testing machine",
            "b) Universal testing machine",
            "c) Rockwell tester",
            "d) Brinell tester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A universal testing machine (UTM), also known as a universal tester, materials testing machine or materials test frame, is used to test the tensile strength and compressive strength of materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The ability of the material to resist stress without failure is called ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Hardness",
            "c) Stiffness",
            "d) Toughness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ability of the material to resist stress without failure is called as strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "In universal testing machine, for a circular section specimen, the gauge length is taken to be ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.65 √A",
            "b) 4.65 √A",
            "c) 5.65 √A",
            "d) 6.65 √A where A is the area of cross section of the specimen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is the formula to find the gauge length when we have the area of the specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "During compression test of cast iron, the failure occurs i.e. the crack appears along the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonal",
            "b) Surface parallel to load applied",
            "c) Surface perpendicular to load applied",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shape of specimen used in compression test is Cube and cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "The property of a material that resists penetration or indentation by means of abrasion or scratching is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Hardness",
            "c) Stiffness",
            "d) Toughness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During compression test of cast iron, the failure occurs i.e. the crack appears along the diagonal."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "The indenter used in Brinell hardness test is a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ball",
            "b) Cone",
            "c) Cylinder",
            "d) Pyramid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The property of a material that resists penetration or indentation by means of abrasion or scratching is known as hardness."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "For hardness test of copper in Brinell hardness tester, the diameter of ball is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7mm",
            "b) 1mm",
            "c) 5mm",
            "d) 3mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Brinell method applies a predetermined test load (F) to a carbide ball of fixed diameter (D) which is held for a predetermined time period and then removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In charpy test specimen, the angle of v-notch section is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 degrees",
            "b) 45 degrees",
            "c) 60 degrees",
            "d) 90 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ASTM E-10 is a standard test for determining the Brinell hardness of metallic materials. The load applied in this test is usually 3,000, 1,500, or 500 kgf, so that the diameter of the indentation is 5 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "When vibrators are used for compaction, the consistency of concrete depends upon the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of mix",
            "b) Efficiency of vibrator",
            "c) Placing conditions",
            "d) Type of mix, efficiency of vibrator, pacing conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Segregation means concrete cement slurry & fine aggregates &coarse aggregate collapsed & have no slump & after hardening no strength but workability is the checking the concrete how much time used after mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct while compacting concrete with vibrators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The vibrator should be inserted horizontally",
            "b) The vibrator should not be immersed through a full depth of freshly laid concrete",
            "c) The vibrator should not touch the form surface",
            "d) The vibrator should touch the form surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When vibrators are used for compaction, the consistency of concrete depends upon the Type of mix, efficiency of vibrator, pacing conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "The levelling operation that removes humps and hollows and give a true, uniform concrete surface is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screeding",
            "b) Floating",
            "c) Troweling",
            "d) Compacting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If there is a considerable amount of time lapse between the placements of subsequent lifts, it may be necessary to re vibrate the previous lift prior to placing additional concrete to minimize the potential for pour lines and cold joints."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "The final operation of finishing the concrete surface is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screeding",
            "b) Floating",
            "c) Troweling",
            "d) Compacting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The levelling operation that removes humps and hollows and give a true, uniform concrete surface is called Screeding."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The process of hardening the concrete mixes by keeping its surface moist for a certain period is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curing",
            "b) Floating",
            "c) Troweling",
            "d) Compacting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The final operation of finishing the concrete surface is called Troweling."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "After the curing of 28 days, the concrete gains strength upto _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40%",
            "b) 60%",
            "c) 80%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of removing the irregularities from the surface of concrete left after screeding is called floating."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The construction joints in cement concrete ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Should be located where bending moment is large",
            "b) Should be located where shear force is large",
            "c) Should not be provided at the corners",
            "d) Should be spaced at a distance of 3 m apart in case of huge structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of hardening the concrete mixes by keeping its surface moist for a certain period is called curing."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "For compacting large sections of mass concrete in structures, the type of vibrator used is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal vibrator",
            "b) External vibrator",
            "c) Screed vibrator",
            "d) Internal and Screed vibrator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After the curing of 28 days, the concrete gains strength upto 100 percentage."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "What is flexural strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stress value obtained when the peak load value is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "b) The stress value representing the average flexural strength in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n obtained when Pe,n is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "c) The load value representing the average load-carrying capacity in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n",
            "d) Value of the mean equivalent flexural strength normalized with respect to mean flexural strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stress value obtained when the peak load value is used in the equation of modulus of rupture is called flexural strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "What is equivalent flexural load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stress value obtained when the peak load value is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "b) The stress value representing the average flexural strength in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n obtained when Pe,n is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "c) The load value representing the average load-carrying capacity in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n",
            "d) Value of the mean equivalent flexural strength normalized with respect to mean flexural strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The load value representing the average load-carrying capacity in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n is equivalent flexural load."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "What is equivalent flexural strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stress value obtained when the peak load value is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "b) The stress value representing the average flexural strength in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n obtained when Pe,n is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "c) The load value representing the average load-carrying capacity in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n",
            "d) Value of the mean equivalent flexural strength normalized with respect to mean flexural strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stress value representing the average flexural strength in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n obtained when Pe,n is used in the equation of modulus of rupture is called equivalent flexural strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "What is equivalent flexural strength ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stress value obtained when the peak load value is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "b) The stress value representing the average flexural strength in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n obtained when Pe,n is used in the equation of modulus of rupture",
            "c) The load value representing the average load-carrying capacity in the post peak region up to a specified deflection of L/n",
            "d) Value of the mean equivalent flexural strength normalized with respect to mean flexural strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Equivalent flexural strength ratio is Value of the mean equivalent flexural strength normalized with respect to mean flexural strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Calipers, capable of reading the dimensions of test specimens to an accuracy of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mm",
            "b) .1mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) .5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Calipers, capable of reading the dimensions of test specimens to an accuracy of 0.1 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Rule (ruler/scale), capable of reading the dimensions of test specimens to an accuracy of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mm",
            "b) .1mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) .5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rule (ruler/scale), capable of reading the dimensions of test specimens to an accuracy of 1 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Load measuring device shall be capable of measuring loads to an accuracy of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1N",
            "b) 10N",
            "c) 1KN",
            "d) 10KN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Load measuring device shall be capable of measuring loads to an accuracy of 10N."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The tolerances on the cross-section of the test specimens shall be within ± ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tolerances on the cross-section of the test specimens shall be within ± 2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "The flexural strength (or modulus of rupture) is obtained for the first peak load, Pmax as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pmax * L/bd2",
            "b) Pmax/Ld2",
            "c) Pmax * L/bd",
            "d) Pmax/L/bd2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It should be noted that the value obtained may be significantly different from that obtained in a conventional test carried out under load control, where the specimen fails at the peak load."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "A data acquisition system capable of digitally recording and storing load and deflection data at least ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 times per sec",
            "b) 5 times per sec",
            "c) 10 times per sec",
            "d) 15 times per sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A data acquisition system capable of digitally recording and storing load and deflection data at least 10 times per second (i.e., a sampling frequency of 10 Hz is suitable."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Ring test is the determination for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compressive strength",
            "b) Tensile strength",
            "c) Both Compressive and tensile strength",
            "d) Flexural strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Malhotra reintroduced another technique, the ring test, for determination of Tensile strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Ring test is not the determination for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breaking Force",
            "b) Tensile strength",
            "c) Ultimate Elongation",
            "d) Compressive strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ring test is used to analysis for Breaking Force, Tensile strength, Ultimate Elongation."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Most small and common ___________ load capacity machines will work for the loads of the materials tested to this specification.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1N",
            "b) 1KN",
            "c) 10N",
            "d) 10KN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most small and common 1kN (225 pound) load capacity machines will work for the loads of the materials tested to this specification."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Begin the test by separating the grips at a speed of  _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm per minute",
            "b) 20 inches per sec",
            "c) 20 inches per minute",
            "d) 20 cm per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Begin the test by separating the grips at a speed of 20 inches per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "At least 30 __________ of crosshead travel or more for high elongation materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cm",
            "b) inches",
            "c) mm",
            "d) m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At least 30 inches of crosshead travel or more for high elongation materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Ring tensile strength is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proportional to time",
            "b) Inversely proportional to time",
            "c) Inversely proportional to hydrostatic pressure",
            "d) Inversely proportional to average diameter of ring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: fr = PD/2t where P = hydrostatic pressure, D= average diameter of ring, t = time."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "The tensile properties of a low-pressure plasma-deposited nickel-base superalloy from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 to 100° C",
            "b) 250 to 1010° C",
            "c) 25 to 1010° C",
            "d) 100 to 250° C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A ring tensile test using a split disc fixture was developed and used to evaluate the tensile properties of a low-pressure plasma-deposited nickel-base superalloy from 25 to 1010° C."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "ASTM D1414 (D 1414) covers multiple properties of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T ring",
            "b) O ring",
            "c) C ring",
            "d) U ring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ASTM D1414 (D 1414) covers multiple properties of O-Rings. Part of the specification includes tension testing for determining the breaking force, tensile strength, and ultimate elongation of an o-ring."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "The tolerances on the cross-section of the test specimens shall be within ± ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tolerances on the cross-section of the test specimens shall be within ± 2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a type of Non-destructive testing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression test",
            "b) Visual testing",
            "c) Ultrasonic testing",
            "d) Eddy current testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compression test is a type of destructive testing. This test is used to determine behavior of metals under compressive load. Visual testing, ultrasonic testing, eddy current testing are types of non-destructive testing."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Identify the type of destructive testing ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiographic test",
            "b) Dye penetrant test",
            "c) Creep test",
            "d) Visual testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Creep test is a type of destructive test. It is defined as slow plastic deformation at high temperatures for a longer time under constant stresses. Creep occurs at room temperature and at high temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the last step in magnetic particle test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Observation and inspection",
            "b) Circular magnetization",
            "c) Demagnetization",
            "d) Magnetization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Different steps involved in magnetic particle test are cleaning the surface, magnetizing the metallic component, application of ferromagnetic powder, observation and inspection and demagnetization."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is/are true for the ultrasonic test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equipment used for ultrasonic testing is portable",
            "b) Complicated shapes can be easily scanned",
            "c) Waves generated are health hazardous",
            "d) Waves generated are health hazardous and complicated shapes can be easily scanned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ultrasonic test uses sound waves of high frequency to detect discontinuities. This method is used to detect flaws on the surface and also deep inside the component. The waves travel in straight line and are reflected from metal gas interface or discontinuities in their patch."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which test can be performed without skilled labour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probe test",
            "b) Bend liquid test",
            "c) Dye penetrant test",
            "d) Torsion test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dye penetrant test does not require any skilled labour. This method only detects surface discontinuities and this test needs to be observed with naked eyes or with a low magnifying glass."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is nondestructive test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nondestructive tests are applications for detecting flaws in materials without impairing their usefulness",
            "b) Nondestructive tests are applications for detecting flaws that impair the use of the materials such as pressure testing",
            "c) Nondestructive tests are applications for detecting flaws in materials with impairing their usefulness",
            "d) Nondestructive tests are applications for detecting flaws that do not impair the use of the materials such as pressure testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nondestructive tests are applications for detecting flaws in materials without impairing their usefulness."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "What is a destructive test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Destructive tests are applications for detecting flaws in materials without impairing their usefulness",
            "b) Destructive tests are applications for detecting flaws that impair the use of the materials such as pressure testing",
            "c) Destructive tests are applications for detecting flaws in materials with impairing their usefulness",
            "d) Destructive tests are applications for detecting flaws that do not impair the use of the materials such as pressure testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Destructive tests are applications for detecting flaws that impair the use of materials such as pressure testing."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "An ultrasonic pulse velocity test is an _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ex-situ, nondestructive test",
            "b) In-situ, nondestructive test",
            "c) Ex-situ, destructive test",
            "d) In-situ, destructive test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An ultrasonic pulse velocity test is an in-situ, nondestructive test to check the quality of concrete and natural rocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "In this test, the strength and quality of concrete or rock is assessed by measuring the ___ of an ultrasonic pulse.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length",
            "b) Velocity",
            "c) Weight",
            "d) Surface Tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this test, the strength and quality of concrete or rock is assessed by measuring the velocity of an ultrasonic pulse passing through a concrete structure or natural rock formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Higher velocities indicate __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good quality and continuity of the material",
            "b) Bad quality and continuity of the material",
            "c) Concrete with many cracks",
            "d) Concrete with many voids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Higher velocities indicate good quality and continuity of the material, while slower velocities may indicate concrete with many cracks or voids."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Slower velocities may indicate ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good quality and continuity of the material",
            "b) Good quality and discontinuity of the material",
            "c) Bad quality and continuity of the material",
            "d) Concrete with many voids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Slower velocities may indicate concrete with many cracks or voids, while higher velocities indicate good quality and continuity of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Mechanical pulse having an oscillation frequency in range of `_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 kHz to 40 kHz",
            "b) 40 kHz to 50 kHz",
            "c) 50 kHz to 60 kHz",
            "d) 60 kHz to 70 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mechanical pulse having an oscillation frequency in range of 40000 Hz to 50000 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "The number of cylces per second is the definition of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wave speed",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Hertz",
            "d) Velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One hertz (Hz) stands for one cycle per second and it is the SI unit of frequency. Velocity means displacement covered per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "A discontinuity that occurs during the casting of molten metal which may be caused by the splashing, surging, interrupted pouring is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burst",
            "b) Cold shut",
            "c) Flaking",
            "d) Blow hole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A discontinuity that occurs during the casting of molten metal which may be caused by the splashing, surging, interrupted pouring, or the meeting of two streams of metal coming from different directions is called cold shut."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "When the motion of the particles of a medium are at right angles to the direction of wave motion, the wave being transmitted is called a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinal wave",
            "b) Shear wave",
            "c) Surface wave",
            "d) Lamb wave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the motion of the particles of a medium are at right angles to the direction of wave motion, the wave being transmitted is called a longitudinal wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "A second name for compression wave is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinal wave",
            "b) Shear wave",
            "c) Surface wave",
            "d) Lamb wave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lamb waves are similar to longitudinal waves, with compression and rarefaction, but they are bounded by the sheet or plate surface causing a wave-guide effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "The interference field near the face of a transducer is often referred to as the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fresnel zone",
            "b) Acoustic impedance",
            "c) Exponential field",
            "d) Phasing zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio frequency line of sight is defined by Fresnel Zones which are ellipse shaped areas between any two radios."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "The _________ compressive strength required from structural consideration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nominal",
            "b) Minimum",
            "c) Maximum",
            "d) No"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Option d can be eliminated easily because we need atleast some compressive strength. The minimum compressive strength required from structural consideration."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "The adequate workability necessary for _________ compaction with the compacting equipment available.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half",
            "b) Quarter",
            "c) Full",
            "d) Double"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option d can be eliminated easily because double compaction is not possible. The adequate workability necessary for full compaction with the compacting equipment available."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "__________ water-cement ratio content to give adequate durability for the particular site conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum",
            "b) Nominal",
            "c) .5",
            "d) Maximum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maximum water-cement ratio and/or maximum cement content to give adequate durability for the particular site conditions. It helps to avoid shrinkage cracking due to temp cycle in mass concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "_________ cement content to avoid shrinkage cracking due to temperature cycle in mass concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum",
            "b) Nominal",
            "c) .5",
            "d) Maximum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maximum cement content to avoid shrinkage cracking due to the temperature cycle in mass concrete. It gives adequate durability for the particular site condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "__________ has designated the concrete mixes into a number of grades as M10, M15.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456-2000",
            "b) IS 456-2010",
            "c) IS 513-1999",
            "d) IS 465-2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 456-2000 has designated the concrete mixes into a number of grades as M10, M15, M20, M25, M30, M35 and M40."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "What is the approx. mix proportion for M10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:3:6",
            "b) 1:2:4",
            "c) 1:1.5:3",
            "d) 1:1:2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to IS 456-2000 code, the approximate value of mix proportion for grade M10 is 1:3:6."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "What is the approx. mix proportion for M15?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:3:6",
            "b) 1:2:4",
            "c) 1:1.5:3",
            "d) 1:1:2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IS 456-2000 code, the approximate value of mix proportion for grade M15 is 1:2:4."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What is the approx. mix proportion for M20?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:3:6",
            "b) 1:2:4",
            "c) 1:1.5:3",
            "d) 1:1:2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IS 456-2000 code, the approximate value of mix proportion for grade M20 is 1:1.5:3."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is the approx. mix proportion for M25?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:3:6",
            "b) 1:2:4",
            "c) 1:1.5:3",
            "d) 1:1:2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to IS 456-2000 code, the approximate value of mix proportion for grade M25 is 1:1:2."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Maximum nominal size of aggregates to be used in concrete may be as large as possible within the limits prescribed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456-2000",
            "b) IS 456-2010",
            "c) IS 513-1999",
            "d) IS 465-2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option can be eliminated because there is no such code. Maximum nominal size of aggregates to be used in concrete may be as large as possible within the limits prescribed by IS 456:2000."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Depending on the degree of workability and placing condition determine the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump value",
            "b) The maximum size of aggregate",
            "c) The amount of mixing water",
            "d) The minimum water-cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slump value is depended on the degree of workability and placing condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Depending on the economical availability and dimensions of the structure determine the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump value",
            "b) The maximum size of aggregate",
            "c) The amount of mixing water",
            "d) The minimum water-cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value for the maximum size of aggregate depends on the economical availability and dimensions of the structure determine."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "For the given slump and maximum size of coarse aggregate determine the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump value",
            "b) The maximum size of aggregate",
            "c) The amount of mixing water",
            "d) The minimum water-cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the given slump and maximum size of coarse aggregate determine the amount of mixing water."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Determine the _______ either from strength considerations or from durability considerations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump value",
            "b) The maximum size of aggregate",
            "c) The amount of mixing water",
            "d) The minimum water-cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Determine the minimum water-cement ratio either from strength considerations or from durability considerations."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Determine the amount of cement per unit volume of concrete from ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slump value",
            "b) The maximum size of aggregate",
            "c) The amount of mixing water",
            "d) The maximum size of aggregate and the amount of mixing water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Determine the amount of cement per unit volume of concrete from the maximum size of aggregate and the amount of mixing water."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "This cement content should ________ the cement content required based on durability criteria.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Be more than",
            "b) Be equal to",
            "c) Be less than",
            "d) Not be less than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This cement content should not be less than the cement content required based on durability criteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "The lower the w/c ratio ___________ the strength of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher",
            "b) Lower",
            "c) Poor",
            "d) Moderate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to ACI mix design, the lower the w/c ratio, higher the strength of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "The aim of the designer should always be to get concrete mixtures of optimum strength at _________ cement content and ________ workability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum, Nonacceptable",
            "b) Minimum, Nonacceptable",
            "c) Maximum, acceptable",
            "d) Minimum, acceptable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The aim of the designer should always be to get concrete mixtures of optimum strength at minimum cement content and acceptable workability.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates should not be larger than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/5 the minimum dimension of structural members",
            "b) 1/4 the minimum dimension of structural members",
            "c) 1/3 the minimum dimension of structural members",
            "d) 1/6 the minimum dimension of structural members"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates should not be larger than 1/5 the minimum dimension of structural members."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates should not be larger than _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/3 the thickness of a slab",
            "b) 1/2 the thickness of a slab",
            "c) 1/1 the thickness of a slab",
            "d) 1/4 the thickness of a slab"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates should not be larger than 1/3 the thickness of a slab."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, Characteristic Flexural Strength at 28 days is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 N/mm2",
            "b) 4.5 N/mm2",
            "c) 5 N/mm2",
            "d) 3.5 N/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, Characteristic Flexural Strength at 28 days is 4.5 N/mm2 and rest all values don’t stand anywhere."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011 _______% Fly ash is required to be replaced with the total cementitious materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, 20% Fly ash is required to be replaced with the total cementitious materials and 25% was according to IRC:15-2002."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2002 _______% Fly ash is required to be replaced with the total cementitious materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2002, 25% Fly ash is required to be replaced with the total cementitious materials and 20% was according to 2011."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2002, Maximum nominal size of aggregates is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm crushed aggregates",
            "b) 31.5 mm crushed aggregates",
            "c) 25 mm crushed aggregates",
            "d) 30.5 mm crushed aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2002, the maximum nominal size of aggregates is 20 mm crushed aggregates and 31.5mm was according to 2011."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, Maximum nominal size of aggregates is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm crushed aggregates",
            "b) 31.5 mm crushed aggregates",
            "c) 25 mm crushed aggregates",
            "d) 30.5 mm crushed aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, the maximum nominal size of aggregates is 31.5 mm crushed aggregates and 20mm was according to 2002."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for OPC shall _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shall not be less than 360 kg/m3",
            "b) Shall not be less than 425 kg/m3",
            "c) Shall not be less than 340 kg/m3",
            "d) Shall not be less than 500 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for OPC shall not be less than 360 kg/ m3 and for pcc it shouldn’t be less than 425 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for PPC  shall _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shall not be less than 360 kg/m3",
            "b) Shall not be less than 425 kg/m3",
            "c) Shall not be less than 340 kg/m3",
            "d) Shall not be less than 500 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for OPC shall not be less than 425 kg/ m3 and for opc it  shouldn’t be less than 360 kg/ m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for OPC + fly ash mix OPC shall ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shall not be less than 360 kg/m3",
            "b) Shall not be less than 425 kg/m3",
            "c) Shall not be less than 340 kg/m3",
            "d) Shall not be less than 500 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, Minimum cement content for 4.5 N/mm2 characteristic flexural strength for OPC + fly ash mix OPC shall not be less than 340 kg/m3 and for opc it  shouldn’t be less than 360 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, maximum free W/C ratio for OPC is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .45",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .55"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, maximum free water cement ratio for Ordinary Portland Cement is .45 and for PPC it’s .5."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "According to IRC:15-2011, maximum free W/C ratio for PPC is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .45",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .55"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IRC:15-2011, maximum free water cement ratio for PPC is .5 and for opc it’s .45. "
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "IS code for Specification for ordinary Portland cement, 33 grade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 269:1989",
            "b) IS 383:197",
            "c) IS 455:1989",
            "d) IS 456:2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 269:1989 code is for specification for ordinary Portland cement of 33 grade. This standard covers the manufacture and chemical and physical requirements of ordinary Portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "IS code for Specification for coarse and fine aggregates from natural sources for concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 269:1989",
            "b) IS 383:197",
            "c) IS 455:1989",
            "d) IS 456:2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS 383:1970 – Specification for coarse and fine aggregates from natural sources for concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "IS code for Specification for Portland slag cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 269:1989",
            "b) IS 383:197",
            "c) IS 455:1989",
            "d) IS 456:2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 455:1989 is for specification for Portland slag cement to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "IS Code of practice for plain and reinforced concrete is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 269:1989",
            "b) IS 383:197",
            "c) IS 455:1989",
            "d) IS 456:2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IS 456:2000 Code of practice for plain and reinforced concrete to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "IS 457:1957 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 457:1957 Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "IS 1489(Part 1):1991 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS 1489(Part 1):1991 Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "IS 1489(Part 2):1991 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 1489(Part 2):1991 Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "IS 1727:1967 is for __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Fly ash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IS 1727:1967 Methods of test for pozzolanic materials to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "IS 650:1991 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specification for standard sand for testing of cement",
            "b) Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete",
            "c) Specification for pozzolana cement",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 650:1991 Specification for standard sand for testing of cement to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "IS 1199:1959 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specification for standard sand for testing of cement",
            "b) Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 1199:1959 Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Loss on Ignition (L.O.I.) is the loss in weight of cement after being heated to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000°C",
            "b) 100°C",
            "c) 500°C",
            "d) 1500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It indicates the prehydration or carbonation due to prolonged or improper storage of cement & clinker."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "On cooling below 1250oC, C3S decomposes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast",
            "b) Slowly",
            "c) Never",
            "d) Depends on the conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On cooling below 1250oC, C3S decomposes slowly but, if cooling is not too slow, C3S remains unchanged and is relatively stable at ordinary temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "If the moisture content of 5 to 10% by weight, then the bulking of sand is increased by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: With the moisture content of 5 to 10% by weight, the bulking of sand is increased by 50."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "When sand is fully dry then it’s volume is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Less",
            "c) More",
            "d) Can’t say"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the sand is fully dry then there is 0 bulking in it. Therefore, the volume of sand will be same."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "The mineral oil if present in mixing for concrete ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves strength",
            "b) Reduces strength",
            "c) Gives more slump",
            "d) Gives a smooth surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mineral oil is present in mixing for concrete increases strength for the concentration up to 2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "To neutralize 200 ml of sample should not require more than 10 ml of __________ normal HCI using methyl orange.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) .1",
            "c) 10",
            "d) .01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To neutralize 200 ml of water sample the value of 0.1 normal HCI using methyl orange as an indicator should not require more than 10 ml."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The loss in weight should not exceed ________ % when tested with Na2SO4 and ________ % with MgSO4 solution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12, 18",
            "b) 18, 12",
            "c) 10, 15",
            "d) 15, 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss in weight should not exceed 12 percent when tested with sodium sulphate and 18 percent with magnesium sulphate solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "In universal testing machine, for a circular section specimen, the gauge length is taken to be _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.65 √A",
            "b) 4.65 √A",
            "c) 5.65 √A",
            "d) 6.65 √A where A is the area of cross section of the specimen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is the formula to find the gauge length when we have the area of the specimen in a universal testing machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "During compression test of cast iron, the failure occurs i.e. the crack appears along the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonal",
            "b) Surface parallel to load applied",
            "c) Surface perpendicular to load applied",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The failure occurs i.e., the crack appears along the diagonal during the compression test of cast iron."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "The indenter used in Brinell hardness test is a ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ball",
            "b) Cone",
            "c) Cylinder",
            "d) Pyramid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Brinell method applies a predetermined test load (F) to a carbide ball of fixed diameter (D) which is held for a predetermined time period and then removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "In charpy test specimen, the angle of v-notch section is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 degrees",
            "b) 45 degrees",
            "c) 60 degrees",
            "d) 90 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In charpy test specimen, the angle of v-notch section is 45 degrees and 0.25mm radius along the base."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "During radiography test, which region absorbs less radiation and transmits more?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low and high density regions absorb and transmit same amount of radiation",
            "b) High density region",
            "c) Low density region",
            "d) Low and high density regions adsorb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This method uses short wavelength electromagnetic radiations such as X-rays and γ rays to detect internal defects. In this method the component to be tested is placed in path of radiations caused due to X-rays or γ rays."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Which test is used to determine the dimensions of any object?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasonic test",
            "b) Torsion test",
            "c) Eddy current test",
            "d) Compression test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Eddy current test is used to determine dimensions of objects, to detect cracks. An eddy current instrument consists of a probe or coil, an electronic unit for generating frequency and a CRT unit for display purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "In which type of test the capillary action principle is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probe test",
            "b) Bend liquid test",
            "c) Dye penetrant test",
            "d) Torsion test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dye penetrant test uses the capillary action principle to detect surface discontinuities. In this method liquid is applied on a metallic surface and it gets entered into cracks which are open. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "What C31 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Making and Curing Concrete Test Specimens in the Field",
            "b) Test Method for Compressive Strength of Cylindrical Specimen",
            "c) Test Method for Unit Weight, Yield, and Air Content (Gravimetric) of Concrete",
            "d) Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C31 test is for Test Method for Making and Curing Concrete Test Specimens in the Field."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "What C39 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Making and Curing Concrete Test Specimens in the Field",
            "b) Test Method for Compressive Strength of Cylindrical Specimen",
            "c) Test Method for Unit Weight, Yield, and Air Content (Gravimetric) of Concrete",
            "d) Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C39 test is for Test Method for Compressive Strength of Cylindrical Specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "What C138 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Making and Curing Concrete Test Specimens in the Field",
            "b) Test Method for Compressive Strength of Cylindrical Specimen",
            "c) Test Method for Unit Weight, Yield, and Air Content (Gravimetric) of Concrete",
            "d) Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C138 test is for Test Method for Unit Weight, Yield, and Air Content (Gravimetric) of Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "What C143 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Making and Curing Concrete Test Specimens in the Field",
            "b) Test Method for Compressive Strength of Cylindrical Specimen",
            "c) Test Method for Unit Weight, Yield, and Air Content (Gravimetric) of Concrete",
            "d) Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C143 test is for Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "What C172 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Sampling Freshly Mixed Concrete",
            "b) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Volumetric Method",
            "c) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Pressure Method",
            "d) Test Method for Temperature of Freshly Mixed Portland-Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C172 test is for Test Method for Sampling Freshly Mixed Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "What C173 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Sampling Freshly Mixed Concrete",
            "b) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Volumetric Method",
            "c) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Pressure Method",
            "d) Test Method for Temperature of Freshly Mixed Portland-Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C173 test is for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Volumetric Method."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "What C 231 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Sampling Freshly Mixed Concrete",
            "b) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Volumetric Method",
            "c) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Pressure Method",
            "d) Test Method for Temperature of Freshly Mixed Portland-Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C231 test is for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Pressure Method."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "What C 1064 test under the Standard ASTM test method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test Method for Sampling Freshly Mixed Concrete",
            "b) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Volumetric Method",
            "c) Test Method for Air Content of Freshly Mixed Concrete by the Pressure Method",
            "d) Test Method for Temperature of Freshly Mixed Portland-Cement Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Standard ASTM test methods to evaluate field-placed concrete C1064 test is for Temperature of Freshly Mixed Portland-Cement Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Generally what is the w/c ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .25",
            "b) .5",
            "c) .75",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally the water cement ratio is .42-.5 and if it exceeds it will create pores in concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Silica fume is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less reactive",
            "b) Neutral",
            "c) More reactive",
            "d) Absent in concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the most beneficial uses for silica fume is in concrete, because of its both properties, it is a very reactive pozzolana."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Content of SiO2 in silica fume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 52%",
            "b) 35%",
            "c) 21.9%",
            "d) 85-97%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The content of SiO2 in silica fume is 85-97%. 35% is the content of SiO2 in Calcareous (ASTM C618 Class C) Fly Ash."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "What is the content of Al2O3 in fly ash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-60%",
            "b) 15-30%",
            "c) Up to 30%",
            "d) 1-7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The content of Al2O3 in fly ash has been tested according to procedures specified in IS: 1727-1967."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "The property of a material that resists penetration or indentation by means of abrasion or scratching is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Hardness",
            "c) Stiffness",
            "d) Toughness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The property of a material that resists penetration or indentation by means of abrasion or scratching is known as hardness."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "During compression test of cast iron, the failure occurs i.e. the crack appears along the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonal",
            "b) Surface parallel to load applied",
            "c) Surface perpendicular to load applied",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The failure occurs i.e. the crack appears along the diagonal during the compression test of cast iron."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "It opens the area of improvement for quality construction rationally based on the documents from ___________ projects.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Previous",
            "b) Next",
            "c) Later",
            "d) Future"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It opens the area of improvement for quality construction rationally based on the documents from previous projects."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "For walls, columns and vertical faces of all structural members, the form work is generally removed after __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 to 48 hours",
            "b) 3 days",
            "c) 7 days",
            "d) 14 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For rapid hardening cement, 3/7 of the above period will be sufficient in all cases except vertical sides of slabs, beams and columns which should be retained for 24 hours."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Quality control helps to ____________ the risks of overdesign that ___________ the overall cost.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximize, Increase",
            "b) Minimize, Increase",
            "c) Maximize, Decrease",
            "d) Minimize, Decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the very basic requirement for the success of any quality control plan is the availability of experienced, knowledgeable and trained personnel at all levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "___________ cost of maintenance of the structure __________ construction due to quality works.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximize, after",
            "b) Minimize, after",
            "c) Maximize, before",
            "d) Minimize, before"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Quality control helps to minimize the risks of overdesign that reduces the overall cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "It __________ job-site concrete handling, and testing procedures to __________ potential liability to the company.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improve, Increase",
            "b) Improve, Decrease",
            "c) Ruin, Decrease",
            "d) Ruin, Increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Minimize the cost of repair and maintenance of the structure after construction due to quality works."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "___________ quality construction ___________ the wastage of materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good, reduce",
            "b) Bad, reduce",
            "c) Good, increase",
            "d) Bad, Decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It improves job-site concrete handling, curing, sampling and testing procedures to reduce potential liability to the company."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Quality management system _________ perception of customers towards company.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves",
            "b) Deprove",
            "c) Recede",
            "d) Worsen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Quality management system improves perception of customers towards company due to credible quality personnel and quality practices."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Good quality construction _________ the wastage of materials, smooth function of the team.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Doesn’t effect",
            "d) Gain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Good quality construction reduces the wastage of materials, smooth function of the team and keeps the construction cost within the limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Quality control helps to ___________ the risks of overdesign that ___________ the overall cost.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximize, Increase",
            "b) Minimize, Increase",
            "c) Maximize, Decrease",
            "d) Minimize, Decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Quality control helps to minimize the risks of overdesign that reduces the overall cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "It opens the area of improvement for quality construction rationally based on the documents from __________ projects.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Previous",
            "b) Next",
            "c) Later",
            "d) Future"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It opens the area of improvement for quality construction rationally based on the documents from previous projects."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "It __________ job-site concrete handling, curing, sampling and testing procedures.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves",
            "b) Deprove",
            "c) Recede",
            "d) Worsen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Quality of construction activities will be tracked by quality management documents and becomes a record for future reference."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "The cement concrete, from which entrained air and excess water are removed after placing it in position, is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum concrete",
            "b) LWC",
            "c) Prestressed concrete",
            "d) Sawdust concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vacuum concrete is the type of concrete in which the excess water is removed for improving concrete strength. The water is removed by use of vacuum mats connected to a vacuum pump."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 3000 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400-510",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 3000 psi is 440-560 pounds per cubic yard and 400-510 is for compressive strength 2500 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "The light-weight concrete is prepared by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixing Portland cement with sawdust in specified proportion in the concrete",
            "b) Using coke-breeze, slag as aggregate in the concrete",
            "c) Mixing Al in the concrete",
            "d) Mixing Fe in the concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The light-weight concrete is prepared by using coke-breeze, cinder or slag as aggregate in the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Aerated Concrete is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very heavy weight",
            "b) Heavy weight",
            "c) Medium weight",
            "d) Light weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aerated concrete is also referred to as gas concrete, foam concrete, cellular concrete. In India, we have at present a few factories manufacturing aerated concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "No fines concrete is manufactured by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) By adding no fines materials from normal concrete",
            "b) By eliminating no fines materials from normal concrete",
            "c) By reducing its strength",
            "d) By increasing its strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Entrainment of air also improves workability and durability to produce such concrete which would have resistance to weathering actions."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Density of no fines concrete with light weight aggregate vary from ________ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1600-1900",
            "b) <300",
            "c) >2500",
            "d) >300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: No fines concrete is one type of light weight concrete. As the name indicates that it is a concrete mix without fine aggregate or sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "What is the value of modulus of elasticity for Sulphur infiltered concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60-115 MPa",
            "b) 10-16 MPa",
            "c) 35-50 GPa",
            "d) 500 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of the density of no fines aggregates with the light weight aggregates vary from less than 300 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Diameter of Round Steel Fiber lies in the range of ________ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3-.5",
            "b) .25-.75",
            "c) .155-.41",
            "d) .25-.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In bridges, High Density Concrete is being used to reduce the number of beams for supporting span."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "The cement concrete, from which entrained air and excess water are removed after placing it in position, is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum concrete",
            "b) LWC",
            "c) Prestressed concrete",
            "d) Sawdust concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vacuum concrete is the type of concrete in which the excess water is removed for improving concrete strength. The water is removed by use of vacuum mats connected to a vacuum pump."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "The removal of excess air after placing concrete helps in increasing the strength of concrete by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15-20%",
            "b) 20-25%",
            "c) 30-50%",
            "d) 50-70%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The removal of excess air after placing concrete helps in increasing the strength of concrete by 15-20%. To attain these positive effects, the typical individual limitation for OPC replacement is commonly estimated to be 15–20% for FA and 40–50% for GGBS."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "The light-weight concrete is prepared by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixing Portland cement with sawdust in specified proportion in the concrete",
            "b) Using coke-breeze, cinder or slag as aggregate in the concrete",
            "c) Mixing aluminum in the concrete",
            "d) Mixing steel in the concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The light-weight concrete is prepared by using coke-breeze, cinder or slag as aggregate in the concrete. Lightweight aggregates used in structural lightweight concrete are typically expanded shale, clay or slate materials that have been fired in a rotary kiln to develop a porous structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The sound absorption coefficient of light weight concrete is nearly __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Thrice",
            "c) Four times",
            "d) Six times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sound absorption coefficient of light weight concrete is nearly twice. Lightweight aggregates used in structural lightweight concrete are typically expanded clay materials that have been heated in a rotary kiln to develop a porous structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "This type of concrete possesses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High insulating property",
            "b) High conducting property",
            "c) Low insulating property",
            "d) Very high insulating property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This type of concrete possesses the high insulating and low conducting property. Thermal insulation is the reduction of heat transfer between objects in the range of radiative influence."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "In making precast structural units for partition and wall lining purposes, the concrete should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum concrete",
            "b) LWC",
            "c) Prestressed concrete",
            "d) Sawdust concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In making precast structural units for partition and wall lining purposes, the concrete should be LWC."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Most low-density aggregates are ________ in origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic",
            "b) Sea water",
            "c) Highly dense area",
            "d) Low dense area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most low-density aggregates are volcanic in origin and include pumice, tuff, scoria, and cinders."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "________ is also something used as the aggregate component of lightweight concretes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conglomerate",
            "b) Gneiss",
            "c) Marble",
            "d) Diatomite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diatomite is also something used as the aggregate component of lightweight concretes. Diatomite is also known as diatomaceous earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "________ is the most commonly used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conglomerate",
            "b) Gneiss",
            "c) Marble",
            "d) Pumice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pumice is the most commonly used and is actually a glass that forms when frothy volcanic eruptions cool quickly into rock."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Aggregates with a specific gravity of _________ are called lightweight aggregates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) <2.4",
            "b) 2.4-2.8",
            "c) >2.8",
            "d) > 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aggregates with a specific gravity of less than 2.4 are called lightweight aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 2500 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400-510",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 2500 psi is 400-510 pounds per cubic yard and 440-560 for compressive strength 3000 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 3000 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400-510",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 3000 psi is 440-560 pounds per cubic yard and 400-510 is for compressive strength 2500 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 4000 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 740-840",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 4000 psi is 530-660 pounds per cubic yard and 400-510 is for compressive strength 2500 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 5000 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400-510",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 5000 psi is 630-750 pounds per cubic yard and 400-510 is for compressive strength 2500 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 6000 psi is _______ pounds per cubic yard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 740-840",
            "b) 440-560",
            "c) 530-660",
            "d) 630-750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 6000 psi is 740-840 pounds per cubic yard and 400-510 is for compressive strength 2500 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 17.24 MPa is _______ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 237-303",
            "b) 261-332",
            "c) 314-392",
            "d) 373-445"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 17.24 MPa is 237-303 kg/m3. 314-392 is the compressive strength of 27.58 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 20.68 MPa is _______ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 237-303",
            "b) 261-332",
            "c) 314-392",
            "d) 373-445"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 20.68 MPa is 261-332 kg/m3. 314-392 is the compressive strength of 27.58 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 27.58 MPa is _______ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 237-303",
            "b) 261-332",
            "c) 314-392",
            "d) 373-445"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 27.58 MPa is 314-392 kg/m3. 261-332 is the compressive strength of 20.68 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 34.47MPa is _______ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 237-303",
            "b) 261-332",
            "c) 314-392",
            "d) 373-445"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 34.47 MPa is 373-445 kg/m3. 314-392 is the compressive strength of 27.58 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Light weight cement content for compressive strength 41.37 MPa is _______ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 237-303",
            "b) 261-332",
            "c) 314-392",
            "d) 439 – 498"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Light weight cement content for compressive strength 41.37 MPa is 439 – 498 kg/m3. 314-392 is the compressive strength of 27.58 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "What is the amount of mixing water used to make LWC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2",
            "b) 2/3",
            "c) 1/4",
            "d) 1/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The general practice for structural light-weight concrete is to mix the aggregate and about 2/3 of the mixing water for a period upto one minute prior to the addition of cement and the balance mixing water."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "What is the normal time to get uniform mixing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 seconds",
            "b) 2 or more minutes",
            "c) 1 minutes",
            "d) 24 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mixing is done continuously as required for homogeneity. Usually, 2 or more minutes are required to get uniform mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "The strength of the resulting concrete is _______ % lower than when dry aggregate is used for the same content.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10",
            "b) 10-15",
            "c) 15-20",
            "d) 0-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It has been seen that the strength of the resulting concrete is about 5 to 10 percent lower than when dry aggregate is used for the same content and workability."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The density of concrete made with saturated aggregate is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Very high",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Moreover, the density of concrete made with saturated aggregate is higher and the durability of such concrete, especially its resistance to frost is lower."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The light-weight concrete is prepared by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixing Portland cement with sawdust in specified proportion in the concrete",
            "b) Using coke-breeze, slag as aggregate in the concrete",
            "c) Mixing Al in the concrete",
            "d) Mixing Fe in the concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The light-weight concrete is prepared by using coke-breeze, cinder or slag as aggregate in the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Aerated Concrete is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very heavy weight",
            "b) Heavy weight",
            "c) Medium weight",
            "d) Light weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aerated concrete is also referred to as gas concrete, foam concrete, cellular concrete. In India we have at present a few factories manufacturing aerated concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Air contents should be _________ % by volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2",
            "b) 2-3",
            "c) 3-4",
            "d) 4-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This type of cement was first of all developed in U.S.A. It is recommended that air contents should be 03-04 % by volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which one is not used as air entraining agents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alumina",
            "b) Natural resins",
            "c) Fats",
            "d) Oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Natural resins, fats, oils are used as air entraining agents not alumina."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Aerated concrete is made in the density of approx. _________ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 150",
            "c) 250",
            "d) 350"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is found that entrainment of air or gas bubbles while applying cement, increases resistance to frost action."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "No fines concrete is manufactured by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) By adding no fines materials from normal concrete",
            "b) By eliminating no fines materials from normal concrete",
            "c) By reducing its strength",
            "d) By increasing its strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: No fines concrete is one type of light weight concrete. As the name indicates that it is a concrete mix without fine aggregate or sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Coarse aggregates which has been used in this is of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 20 mm",
            "c) 15 mm",
            "d) 25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normally coarse aggregates passing from 20 mm sieve and retained on 10 mm sieve which is further used for this type of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "The w/c ratio is kept in the range of  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) .1-.2",
            "b) .38-.52",
            "c) .83-1",
            "d) .25-.38"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water cement ratio is kept within the range of 0.38-0.52. The water cement ratio should be chosen very carefully considering the cohesive nature of the materials which we are using."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Density of no fines concrete with normal aggregate vary from _________ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1600-1900",
            "b) <300",
            "c) >2500",
            "d) >300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of the density of no fines aggregates with the normal aggregates vary from 1600-1900 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Density of no fines concrete with light weight aggregate vary from _________ kg/m3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1600-1900",
            "b) <300",
            "c) >2500",
            "d) >300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of the density of no fines aggregates with the light weight aggregates vary from less than 300 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "The compressive strength of no fines concrete varies between __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-5 MPa",
            "b) 4-14 MPa",
            "c) 25 MPa",
            "d) >15 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The compressive strength of no fines concrete varies between the ranges of 4MPa to 14 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the disadvantages of this concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lightweight",
            "b) Low strength",
            "c) Low shrinkage",
            "d) Good thermal insulating property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main disadvantage of this concrete is that it has very low strength as compared to ordinary Portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of this concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low density",
            "b) Low strength",
            "c) It can’t be use in RCC structure",
            "d) Cannot be measured by any available standard methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to low density i.e., it is light weight which is good for our construction purpose because it will be easy to transport."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The range of the density for this concrete is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) >5000 kg/cu. m",
            "b) <6000 kg/cu m",
            "c) 3400-5600 kg/cu m",
            "d) <3400 kg/cu m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Test results indicate that high density concrete with densities ranging from 3400 -5600 kg/cu m."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The compressive strength varies from  ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) < 200 kg/cm2",
            "b) > 550 kg/cm2",
            "c) 200-550 kg/cm2",
            "d) 700 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compressive strengths varying from 200 -550 kg/sq cm can be produced using steel punchings as coarse aggregate."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Due to low w/c ratio _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It doesn’t cause any problems",
            "b) It causes problems",
            "c) Workability is easy",
            "d) Strength is more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to low water cement ratio, it causes many problems that’s why superplasticizers are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates are used to produce 70MPa compressive strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20-30 mm",
            "b) 10-20 mm",
            "c) 30-40 mm",
            "d) 40-50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates is 20-30 mm are used to produce 70MPa compressive strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregates are used to produce 100MPa compressive strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20-30 mm",
            "b) 10-20 mm",
            "c) 30-40 mm",
            "d) 40-50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum size of aggregates is 10-20 mm are used to produce 100MPa compressive strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Main component in this concrete is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cement",
            "b) Sulphur",
            "c) Sulphur and aggregates",
            "d) Aggregates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sulphur concrete is a composite construction material, composed mainly of sulphur and aggregate (generally a coarse aggregate made of gravel or crushed rocks and a fine aggregate such as sand)."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "What is the compressive strength of this concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60-115 MPa",
            "b) 10-16 MPa",
            "c) 35-50 GPa",
            "d) 500 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 60-115 MPa is the compressive strength of the Sulphur concrete where as OPC has 15-60 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "What is the bending strength of this concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60-115 MPa",
            "b) 10-16 MPa",
            "c) 35-50 GPa",
            "d) 500 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 10-16 MPa is the bending strength of the Sulphur Infiltered concrete where as OPC has 6-7 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "What is the value of modulus of elasticity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60-115 MPa",
            "b) 10-16 MPa",
            "c) 35-50 GPa",
            "d) 500 GPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 35-60 GPa is the range of modulus of elasticity for the Sulphur infiltered concrete whereas the OPC has the range of 25-28 GPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "What is the range of contraction for this concrete in mm/m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5-1",
            "b) .6",
            "c) <1",
            "d) >1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 0.5-1 mm/m is the range of contraction for Sulphur infiltered concrete where as .6mm/m is for OPC."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "What is the linear coefficient of thermal expansibility for this concrete in 10-6/K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8-12",
            "b) 8-10",
            "c) 10-15",
            "d) 12-15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 8*10-6/K to 12*10-6/K is the linear coefficient of thermal expansibility for sulphur infiltered concrete where as 8*10-6/K to 10*10-6/K is for OPC."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "What is the density for this concrete in kg/m3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2400",
            "b) 2200",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 2400 kg/m3 is the density for sulphur infiltered concrete 2200 kg/m3 is the density of Ordinary Portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "_______ % is the range for porosity of this concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 0-1",
            "d) 9-15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 1 % to 4% is the range for porosity of sulphur infiltered concrete and 9% to 15 % is the range for OPC."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "_______ % is the range for absorptivity of this concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 0-1",
            "d) 9-15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 0 % to 1% is the range for absorptivity of Sulphur in filtered concrete and 5 % is the range for OPC."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Diameter of Round Steel Fiber lies in the range of _______ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3-.5",
            "b) .25-.75",
            "c) .155-.41",
            "d) .25-.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Round steel fiber are commonly used and produced by cutting round wire into the short length. The diameter lies in the range of 0.25mm to 0.75mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of the steel fiber after silting in mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3-.5",
            "b) .25",
            "c) .155-.41",
            "d) .25-.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steel fibers having a rectangular cross section are produced by silting the sheets about 0.25mm thick."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of the flat sheet fibers after silting in mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3-.5",
            "b) .25",
            "c) .15-.41",
            "d) .25-.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 0.15 mm to 0.41 mm is the thickness of the flat sheet fibers produced by silting of flat sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "What is the width of the flat sheet fibers after silting in mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3-.5",
            "b) .25",
            "c) .15-.41",
            "d) .25-.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 0.25 mm to 0.90 mm is the width of the flat sheet fibers produced by silting of flat sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Glass fiber is made up from _______ individual filaments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-200",
            "b) 200-400",
            "c) 500",
            "d) >500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polypropylene fibers is hydrophobic in nature that’s why they can be easily mixed as they do not need long time during mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "What is the 10 day compressive failure stress in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 3.4",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This test is based on ASTM C473 – 07 and the 10 day compressive failure stress is 40 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "What is the 10 day compressive young’s modulus in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 3.4",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This test is based on ASTM C473 – 07 and the 10 day compressive young’s modulus is 1500 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "What is the 10 day bending failure stress in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 3.4",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This test is based on BS EN 12467:2004 and the 10 day bending failure stress is 3.4 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "What is the 10 day bending young’s modulus in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 3.4",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This test is based on BS EN 12467:2004 and the 10 day bending young’s modulus is 180 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "What is the 7th day compressive failure stress in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 38",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This test is based on ASTM C473 – 07 and the 7th day compressive failure stress is 38 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "What is the 7 day bending failure stress in N/mm2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 3.3",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This test is based on BS EN 12467:2004 and the 7 day bending failure stress is 3.3 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "___________ mm thickness is not available in concrete cloth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 13",
            "d) 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Concrete cloth is usually available in 3 thicknesses i.e., 5mm, 8mm and 13 mm whereas theoretically there is no limit in the thickness of concrete cloth and typical thickness lies in 2mm to 15 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "________ viscosity liquid monomers are impregnated with the hardened cement composite structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) 0",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For making the polymer impregnated concrete, the pre-polymers or the low viscosity liquid monomers are partially or fully impregnated with the hardened cement composite structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Water-filled voids ranges from _______ % of the total volume of the component for dense concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 15",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Water-filled voids ranges from 5 % of the total volume of the component for dense concrete where as 15 % is for gap-graded concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Water-filled voids ranges from _______ % of the total volume of the component for gap-graded concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 15",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Water-filled voids ranges from 15 % of the total volume of the component for gap-graded concrete where as 5 % is for dense concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "What is the time required to give heating to remove the moisture from the concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6-8 hrs",
            "b) 10 hrs",
            "c) 24 hrs",
            "d) 48 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 6 to 8 hours are must to give heat supply to remove the moisture from the Polymer Impregnated Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "At what temperature the heat is supplied to concrete to remove moisture in oC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35",
            "b) 120-150",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 60-150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  120 oC to 150 oC is the temperature required to give the heating to remove moisture in Polymer Impregnated Concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Which temperature avoids flammability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35",
            "b) 120-150",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 60-150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 35 oC is the temperature that helps to avoid flammability and at that temperature cooling is done after the complete removal of moisture."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The moisture content of the aggregate shall not exceed from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .1% – .5%",
            "b) 1% – 55",
            "c) 10% – 50%",
            "d) 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It was recommend by the scientist later on that the moisture content of the aggregates shall not exceed from .1% to .5%."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which one is not the polymeric resin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyester resin",
            "b) Epoxy resin",
            "c) Vinyl ester resin",
            "d) Sulphates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polymeric resins that are commonly used in polymer concrete are methacrylate, polyester resin, epoxy resin, vinyl ester resin, and furan resins."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Higher resin dosage is recommended when using ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coarse aggregate",
            "b) Fine aggregates",
            "c) All in one aggregates",
            "d) More cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Higher resin dosage is recommended when using fine aggregate, because of the presence of the large surface area of the materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "The addition of glass fibers are in the range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-6%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 15-20%",
            "d) 20%-25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel fibers, glass fibers, carbon fibers, and polyester fibers have been added to in PIC for enhancement of its properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Concrete is not recommended to be placed at a temperature below __________oC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the studies have reported the addition of glass fibers are in the range of 0-6% in PIC."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "IS: 7861 part-2 deals with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot weathering concrete",
            "b) Cold weathering concrete",
            "c) Air entertained concrete",
            "d) OPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Any concreting operation done at a temperature below 5oC is termed as cold weather concreting."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Why the time period for removal of form work has to be increased.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The development of strength of concrete is retarded compared with development at normal temperature",
            "b) The development of strength of concrete is accelerate compared with development at normal temperature",
            "c) The development of strength of concrete is advanced compared with development at normal temperature",
            "d) The development of strength of concrete is precocious compared with development at normal temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS: 7861 part-1 deals with hot weather concreting and Part-2 deals with cold weather concreting."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "If concrete is exposed to repeated freezing and thawing after the final set, the final qualities of the concrete may also be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impair",
            "b) Aid",
            "c) Improve",
            "d) Extend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the temperature is falling to about 50C or below, the development of strength of concrete is retarded compared with development at normal temperature. Thus, the time period for removal of form work has to be increased."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Large temperature differentials within the concrete member may promote __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic shrinkage",
            "b) Cracking",
            "c) High workability",
            "d) Good strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If concrete is exposed to repeated freezing and thawing after the final set and during the hardening period, the final qualities of the concrete may also be impaired."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "When the concrete in fresh stage is exposed to freeze before certain pre-hardening period, compressive strength may get __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased to 50%",
            "b) Decreased to 50%",
            "c) Increased to 25%",
            "d) Decreased to 25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Large temperature differentials within the concrete member may promote cracking and affect its durability adversely."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Concrete is not recommended to be placed at a temperature above _________oC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any operation of concreting done at atmospheric temperature above 40 oC may be put under hot weather concreting."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "IS: 7861 part-1 deals with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot weathering concrete",
            "b) Cold weathering concrete",
            "c) Air entertained concrete",
            "d) OPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS: 7861 part-1 deals with hot weather concreting and Part-2 deals with cold weather concreting."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "A higher temperature of fresh concrete results in a __________ hydration of cement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) More rapid",
            "b) Rapid",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A higher temperature of fresh concrete results in a more rapid hydration of cement and leads to reduced workability/ accelerated setting."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Rapid evaporation may cause plastic shrinkage __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic shrinkage",
            "b) Plastic shrinkage",
            "c) High workability",
            "d) Good strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A higher temperature of fresh concrete results in a more rapid hydration of cement and leads to reduced workability/ accelerated setting. This reduces the handling time of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Prepacked concrete _________ water proofing concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is",
            "b) Is not",
            "c) May be",
            "d) Is but depends on temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rapid evaporation may cause plastic shrinkage and cracking and subsequent cooling of hardened concrete would introduce tensile stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Cement has ________ % volumetric shrinkage after curing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is difficult to retain moisture for hydration and maintain reasonably uniform temperature conditions during the curing period."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "After vacuum mixing, the volumetric shrinkage can be raised from 3–5% to __________ % in different cements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2",
            "b) 3-5",
            "c) 5-7",
            "d) 6-8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prepacked concrete is water proofing concrete with quality plaster which prevents water seepage."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Vacuum mixing systems reduce the exposure by _________ %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option a is the correct one because cement has 3-5% volumetric shrinkage after curing."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The exposure of conventional mixing in open bowl is about ___________ ppm in the breathing zone.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volumetric shrinkage can be raised from 3–5 % to 5-7 % in different cements after mixing vacuum into it."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The __________ compressive strength required from structural consideration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nominal",
            "b) Minimum",
            "c) Maximum",
            "d) No"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Option d can be eliminated easily because we need atleast some compressive strength. The minimum compressive strength required from structural consideration."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "The adequate workability necessary for ___________ compaction with the compacting equipment available.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half",
            "b) Quarter",
            "c) Full",
            "d) Double"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option d can be eliminated easily because double compaction is not possible. The adequate workability necessary for full compaction with the compacting equipment available."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "___________ water-cement ratio content to give adequate durability for the particular site conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum",
            "b) Nominal",
            "c) .5",
            "d) Maximum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maximum water-cement ratio and/or maximum cement content to give adequate durability for the particular site conditions. It helps to avoid shrinkage cracking due to the temp cycle in mass concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "_______ cement content to avoid shrinkage cracking due to temperature cycle in mass concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum",
            "b) Nominal",
            "c) .5",
            "d) Maximum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maximum cement content to avoid shrinkage cracking due to temperature cycle in mass concrete. It gives adequate durability for the particular site condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "________ has designated the concrete mixes into a number of grades as M10, M15.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456-2000",
            "b) IS 456-2010",
            "c) IS 513-1999",
            "d) IS 465-2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 456-2000 has designated the concrete mixes into a number of grades as M10, M15, M20, M25, M30, M35 and M40."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Maximum nominal size of aggregates to be used in concrete may be as large as possible within the limits prescribed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456-2000",
            "b) IS 456-2010",
            "c) IS 513-1999",
            "d) IS 465-2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Option can be eliminated because there is no such code. Maximum nominal size of aggregates to be used in concrete may be as large as possible within the limits prescribed by IS 456:2000."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Identify the type of destructive testing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiographic test",
            "b) Dye penetrant test",
            "c) Creep test",
            "d) Visual testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Creep test is a type of destructive test. It is defined as slow plastic deformation at high temperatures for a longer time under constant stresses. Creep occurs at room temperature and at high temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which test can be performed without skilled labor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probe test",
            "b) Bend liquid test",
            "c) Dye penetrant test",
            "d) Torsion test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dye penetrant test does not require any skilled labor. This method only detects surface discontinuities and this test needs to be observed with naked eyes or with low magnifying glass."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Compressive strength of hardened concrete is done by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cube test",
            "b) Tensile splitting test",
            "c) Concrete core test",
            "d) Flexure test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compressive strength of hardened concrete is done by cube test. For cube test two types of specimens either cubes of 15cm X 15cm X 15cm or 10cm X 10cm x 10cm depending upon the size of aggregate are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "In the soundness test a specimen of hardened cement paste is _______ for a fixed time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze",
            "b) Dry",
            "c) Boiled",
            "d) Dipped in water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A specimen of hardened cement paste is boiled for a fixed time so that if there is any tendency of increase or decrease in size can be detected."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "On cooling below 1250oC, C3S decomposes ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast",
            "b) Slowly",
            "c) Never",
            "d) Depends on the conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On cooling below 1250oC, C3S decomposes slowly but, if cooling is not too slow, C3S remains unchanged and is relatively stable at ordinary temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "The loss in weight should not exceed ______ percent when tested with sodium sulphate and ______ percent with magnesium sulphate solution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12, 18",
            "b) 18, 12",
            "c) 10, 15",
            "d) 15, 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss in weight should not exceed 12 percent when tested with sodium sulphate and 18 percent with magnesium sulphate solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "In a dry environment, concrete strength will be loosed as much as __________ % in moist environment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Laboratory tests show that concrete strength will be loosed as much as 50% in dry environment as compared to moist environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "After finishing concrete surface must be kept __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry",
            "b) First dry it and then wet it",
            "c) First wet it and then dry it",
            "d) Wet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After finishing concrete surface must be kept wet, so that it’d be prevented from evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "A ___________ paste structure undergoes ___________ creep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good, high",
            "b) Poor, high",
            "c) Good, average",
            "d) Poor, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of paste content and its quality is one of the most important factors influencing creep. A poorer paste structure undergoes higher creep."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "SCC has __________ yield stress.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) High",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Self-consolidating concrete or self-compacting concrete (commonly called as SCC) is a concrete mix which has a low yield stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "SCC has __________ deformability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) High",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Self-consolidating concrete or self-compacting concrete (commonly called as SCC) is a concrete mix which has a high deformability."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "SCC has __________ viscosity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) High",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Self-consolidating concrete or self-compacting concrete (commonly called as SCC) is a concrete mix which has a medium viscosity."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "SCC has ___________ segregation resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good",
            "b) Bad",
            "c) Average",
            "d) Poor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Self-consolidating concrete or self-compacting concrete (commonly called as SCC) is a concrete mix that has a medium viscosity and good segregation resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "SCC is measured using the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Picat’s apparatus",
            "b) Slump-flow test",
            "c) Slump test",
            "d) Standard Consistency Test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SCC is measured using Slump flow test rather than usual slump test, as it is too fluid to keep its shape when the cone is removed from it."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "IS code for Specification for ordinary Portland cement, 33 grade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 269:1989",
            "b) IS 383:197",
            "c) IS 455:1989",
            "d) IS 456:2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 269:1989 code is for specification for ordinary Portland cement of 33 grade. This standard covers the manufacture and chemical and physical requirements of ordinary Portland cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "IS 457:1957 is for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 457:1957 Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "IS 1489(Part 1):1991 is for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS 1489(Part 1):1991 Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "IS 1489(Part 2):1991 is for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Flyash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 1489(Part 2):1991 Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "IS 1727:1967 is for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Code of practice for general construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
            "b) Specification for Portland pozzolana cement Part 1 Fly ash based",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanic materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IS 1727:1967 Methods of test for pozzolanic materials to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": " IS 650:1991 is for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specification for standard sand for testing of cement",
            "b) Methods of samplingand analysis of concrete",
            "c) Specification for pozzolana cement",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanicmaterials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 650:1991 Specification for standard sand for testing of cement to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "IS 1199:1959 is for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specification for standard sand for testing of cement",
            "b) Methods of samplingand analysis of concrete",
            "c) Specification for Portland-pozzolana cement: Part 2 Calcined clay based",
            "d) Methods of test for pozzolanicmaterials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS 1199:1959 Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete to the need of civil engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "What is the moisture content in slurry for wet process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35-50%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 40-45%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moisture content in slurry for wet process is 35-50%. 12% is the moisture content for dry process."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Dry intervals in surface wetting leads to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cracking",
            "b) Fogging",
            "c) High strength",
            "d) Good workability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of crushed aggregates may results in 10 to 20% higher compressive strength due to development of stronger aggregate-mortar bond."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The rate of creep rapidly ___________ with time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Doesn’t affect",
            "d) Depends on the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry intervals or patches can lead to crazing or cracking on the slab surface. The effect of surface wettability on the dynamics of crack formation and their characteristics are examined during the drying of aqueous colloidal droplets containing nano particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "The rate of creep generally ____________ with the ____________ of the size of aggregates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase, increase",
            "b) Decrease, decease",
            "c) Increase, decrease",
            "d) 2.5, 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of creep rapidly decreases with time. The time taken by a concrete structure to attained creep is 5 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Reduction in the volume due to shrinkage causes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low volume",
            "b) Volumetric strain",
            "c) Volumetric stress",
            "d) W/c ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rate of creep generally decreases with the increase of the size of aggregates. Time rate of deformation of a material subject to stress at a constant temperature. It is the slope of the creep vs. time diagram obtained in a creep test."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Symptoms for acid attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will show disintegration of the concrete evidenced by loss of the cement paste",
            "b) It will show concrete surfaces that are very rough in areas where the paste is leached",
            "c) Affected concrete does not exhibit telltale features too distinctly",
            "d) Expansion does not occur without reaction products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acid attack will show disintegration of the concrete evidenced by loss of the cement paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Symptoms for aggressive water attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will show disintegration of the concrete evidenced by loss of the cement paste",
            "b) It will show concrete surfaces that are very rough in areas where the paste is leached",
            "c) Affected concrete does not exhibit telltale features too distinctly",
            "d) Expansion does not occur without reaction products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It will show concrete surfaces that are very rough in areas where the paste is leached."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Symptoms for aggressive ACR reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will show disintegration of the concrete evidenced by loss of the cement paste",
            "b) It will show concrete surfaces that are very rough in areas where the paste is leached",
            "c) Affected concrete does not exhibit telltale features too distinctly",
            "d) Expansion does not occur without reaction products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ACR affected concrete does not exhibit telltale features too distinctly. AAR results in deleterious expansive cracking of concrete occurring at the later ages after construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Symptoms for aggressive ASR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will show disintegration of the concrete evidenced by loss of the cement paste",
            "b) It will show concrete surfaces that are very rough in areas where the paste is leached",
            "c) Affected concrete does not exhibit telltale features too distinctly",
            "d) Expansion does not occur without reaction products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Harmful ASR expansion does not occur without reaction products. But reaction products can occur without harmful ASR expansion."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "What should be the minimum water cement ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .45",
            "b) .5",
            "c) <.45",
            "d) >.45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete should be workable with minimum water cement ratio (< 0.45). It should be well compacted by vibrator."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Cement not more than ________ months old should be used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cement not more than 3 months old should be used. Proper cement to be used to prevent sulphate and chloride attack."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Powder epoxy is fusion bonded to bar at about _________0C temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 250",
            "c) 300",
            "d) 350"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fusion bonded epoxy coating process has good results in protecting reinforcement bars from corrosion. Powder epoxy is fusion bonded to bar at about 2500C temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "At the construction stage, binding wires ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Should touch the formwork",
            "b) Should not touch the formwork",
            "c) To be turned outside",
            "d) To be turned whole structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Binding wires to be turned inside (should not touch formwork). G.I. wires to be used in aggressive environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Creep is ____ to the strength of concrete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Similar",
            "c) Directly proportional",
            "d) Inversely proportional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Creep increases with increase in water/cement ratio. In other words, it can also be said that creep is inversely proportional to the strength of concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "How can we prevent cracks in concrete structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to heavy load",
            "b) Low w/c ratio",
            "c) Settlement of structure",
            "d) High water cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low w/c ratio will directly affect the quality of concrete. A lower water cement ratio leads to high strength in concrete therefore lesser cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "What is the maximum w/c ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .2",
            "b) .3",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water cement ratio should not exceed .5 in concreting because it will reduces the workability of the concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which can be the possible option for cracking in the building?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to light load",
            "b) Low w/c ratio",
            "c) Temperature difference",
            "d) Gain of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete expands and shrinks when the temperature changes which directly leads to cracking in the building."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Is it possible to have 0% crack in our building?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yes",
            "b) No",
            "c) May be",
            "d) Can’t be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is not possible to have 0 % cracks in any building after construction. We can prevent it but we can’t stop it."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Plastic shrinkage cracking occurs in ________ hours after placing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5",
            "b) 24",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plastic shrinkage concrete occurs within 1 hours and 8 hours after placing, when subjected to a very rapid loss of moisture."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which one can’t be the reason for the shrinkage of concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) W/c ratio",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Cement content",
            "d) Formwork"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Formwork can never cause shrinkage in concrete even it helps to reduce the shrinkage in concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Evaluation of cracks ________ be determined before cracking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can",
            "b) Can’t",
            "c) Sometimes",
            "d) Depends on the structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Evaluation of cracks can be determined before cracking i.e., due to plastic and constructional movements."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Compressive strength of hardened concrete is done by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cube test",
            "b) Tensile splitting test",
            "c) Concrete core test",
            "d) Flexure test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compressive strength of hardened concrete is done by cube test. For cube test two types of specimens either cubes of 15cm X 15cm X 15cm or 10cm X 10cm x 10cm depending upon the size of aggregate are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "It is about __________ times the tensile stress determined by the splitting test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) .5",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The theoretical maximum tensile stress at the bottom face at failure is calculated. This is termed the modulus of rupture. It is about 1.5 times the tensile stress determined by the splitting test."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "A ratio of core height-to-diameter of __________ gives a standard cylinder test.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A ratio of core height-to-diameter of 2 gives a standard cylinder test. The ratio of core height to diameter and the location where the core is taken affect the strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "In Concrete core test the strength is ________ at the top and _________ at the bottom.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lowest, lowest",
            "b) Lowest, highest",
            "c) Highest, lowest",
            "d) Highest, highest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strength is lowest at the top surface and increases with depth through the element."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Which of the following compound is used for fine polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum oxide",
            "b) Nitric oxide",
            "c) Silicon carbide",
            "d) Iron oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Powder form of aluminum oxide is used for fine polishing process. It is surface treatment process."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Evaluation of cracks _________ be determined after cracking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can",
            "b) Can’t",
            "c) Sometimes",
            "d) Depends on the structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Evaluation of cracks can be determined after cracking i.e., due to structural, thermal, chemical, physical activities."
    }
]